Or for any realistic deep learning setting.
I'm claiming.
On the left, I'm gonna plot the train loss, and on
the right, I'm gonna plot the top eigenvalue of the
Hessian. So let's
start training. And as we train, we can
see the loss goes down
and the sharpness
goes up. Now we don't know
why the sharpness is going up.
This is still unexplained. It
seems to be a very robust property of deep learning objectives.
But the sharpness goes up. And
at some point, gradient descent leaves the stable region.
And so at this point, there's now a direction
in weight space that's too sharp
for our current learning rate.
And we know that on a quadratic,
like on the local quadratic Taylor approximation,
grading descent would oscillate and blow up.
So the question is, what's gonna happen?
On the on the real objective?
Okay. So let's run gradient
descent for the next several steps.
And on the right, I'm gonna plot
Zero. From
along the top eigenvector of the Hessian.
From, like, measured relative to, like,
the start of this animation. So it's
just this quantity. We'll
use the u t zero as the top eigenvector.
This is like the thing that we, expect to oscillate.
According to our local quadratic model.
Okay. So let me start running.
And we can see
that we we are indeed
oscillating along the top eigenvector. As one would
expect. So we're doing this along
the highest curvature direction.
And the oscillations start small, but
they eventually get because they're growing exponentially,
they eventually get so big that the train loss
starts to go up rather than down.
Which is not good. And so the question is, what's
gonna happen next?
Is training gonna succeed?
If so, it's not clear how it can succeed.
Because remember, as long as the sharpness is
above this, two over eight line,
we expect the oscillations along the top I conjecture
to keep growing exponentially.
So it's not clear how things
are gonna stay okay.
So let's see what happens next. I'm
gonna run for several more iterations.
So what's happened? The sharpness
has dropped.
Which is very nice because that's just what we needed
to happen. And
once and in in fact, the sharpness
falls all the way below two of her ADA. A.
Once the sharpness goes below two over eight
a, dynamics along the top eigenvector become
contractive. Again, that makes
sense. And the loss comes back down. That
also makes sense because those we both expect from like
a local quadratic story. The question
though is why did the sharpness drop
just when we needed it to?
Did we get lucky?
Is this something we can expect?
So that was just the beginning
of the trajectory. Now let me show the full trajectory
of gradient descent.
So the sharpness goes up to two over e dah.
And then after it reaches two over eight, it stops
going up further and instead equilibrates
around that value.
Meanwhile, the losses going down over the long
run but it's behaving non monotonically
over the short run.
Let's try different learning rate. That
was learning rate o point o two. Let's now
try a learning rate of half that size, o point o one.
So in orange, I've drawn the new two over ADA.
And we see that
the same thing happens. So
the sharpness goes up to new two of her Ada, and then equilibrates
there. So in other
words, to go back to the beginning, if the expectation
is that gradient descent is starting and
remaining inside the stable region,
the reality seems to be that it's actually tending
to leave the stable region
but whenever it leaves, it
somehow steers itself
back inside.
So how is that
happening?
We call this training at the edge of stability.
So and this behavior is not
specific to that
particular network and
data set, Rather, I'm claiming that this is
the typical behavior of gradient descent
in deep learning. So
here I'm showing you three image tasks.
Three three image architectures on an
image task. You see the same thing is happening.
Here, I'm showing you, three sequence architectures
on a sequence task. Same thing's happening.
So I'm not saying oh, wow, if you
like set up things in this weird way,
this is some weird edge case that you
can force. Rather, I'm saying that this is
the typical behavior of gradient descent.
Now, when I say gradient descent, I mean gradient
descent. And the reason why your runs
don't look exactly like this because you're not using gradient
descent. You're using maybe stochastic
gradient descent, or Adam, or now muon.
But what I'm claiming is if you used gradient descent
as the optimizer, but kept everything else
the same, this is what your training would look like.
That's what I'm claiming.
So the question is, what's going on?
We ask this question in our paper several
years ago,
Why is gradient descent working if not for any
reason we can find in the literature on optimization?
So the answer, in my in my
opinion, a great answer was
given by the subsequent paper,
by Alex Damien, Ashaun Nachani, and Jason
Lee. And what they pointed out
is this,
to understand the dynamics that we just
saw, all you need to do
is tailor expand to one order
higher. Than is normally used when analyzing
first order methods. That's
it. So this tailor expansion so we're gonna
need to tailor expand a third order in the loss.
So this Taylor expansion reveals
the crucial ingredient that's missing
from current optimization theory.
Without this ingredient, you can't understand the behavior
of gradient descent. In deep learning. With it,
you can.
The key fact is that oscillations
along the top eigenvector of the Hessian
automatically induce reduction
the top eigenvalue of the Hessian.
So let's let me sketch that informally. You
can see their paper for a
more formal treatment.
So suppose we're moving through weight space and we're oscillating
along the top eigenvector of the Hessian.
Which is like the vertical direction here.
So let w star
denote the point where you'd be if we if we were not oscillating.
And let w denote the point where you'd
be where we are because we are oscillating.
So in other words, because we're oscillating,
we're displaced from w star
along the u direction by some magnitude.
Let's call that x.
So how does the gradient where we are
w star plus x u, relate to the gradient
at w star is
where we'd be if we were not oscillating.
So by Taylor expand let's let's do
Taylor expansion. Gonna tailor expand Noblal
the gradient map around w
star. So
okay. First term is not very interesting, just gradient
w star. Next term,
which is first order in the gradient or second order
in the loss, says that the gradient
w star plus x u has a term that
is like Hessian at w star,
times x u. That should make sense
because the Heshn is the derivative of the gradient.
But we can simplify that further because
u is an eigenvector of the Hessian,
particular, it's an eigen value eigenvector
whose eigenvalue is s, the sharpness,
So Heshin times u is just sharpness times
u. And sharpness
is a scalar. So this is a
vector that's pointing in the u direction.
And when we follow the negative gradient, this
term's gonna send us into the minus
u direction. So this is just the term that's causing
the oscillations. As we already
expected The magic
quote unquote, is coming from
the next term, in the Taylor expansion of
the gradient. So the next
term looks like this, me unpack
it. This is the curvature in
the u direction. U transpose hessian
u. This is the gradient of
that. So the gradient of the curvature in the
u direction. The curvature
in the u direction well, because you as a top
eigenvector of the Hessian, this is just the top
eigenvalue of the Hessian. Or the
sharpness. And moreover, you can
show that the grading of the curvature
e, e, direction, is just the gradient of
the sharpness.
In other words, just by
tailor expanding, we see that the gradient at w star
plus x u contains the
term that is proportional
to the grading of the sharpness.
Thus, when we take a negative gradient
step at w star plus x u,
it's gonna automatically take
a negative gradient step on the sharpness.
And the step size, quote unquote, of this
negative gradient step is one
half eta x squared where remember that x
squared is the squared magnitude of the oscillation.
So the larger the oscillation, the stronger the
implicit gradient step on the sharpness.
So in other words,
we already knew that sharpness generates
oscillations. But
now what we see from this third order expansion
is that there's also an arrow in the other
direction, where oscillations reduce
sharpness. So you
can think of this as a negative feedback loop.
Yeah. When the sharpness exceeds two over eight, grading
descent oscillates along the top eigenvector,
but in turn, those oscillations
automatically perform gradient descent on the sharpness.
Thereby allowing gradient descent
to automatically remain inside the stable region.
So let me revisit the behavior of gradient descent
that we saw before. So
initially, when the sharpness is bigger than two of
VARTA, that leads to
exponentially growing oscillations. But in
turn, the oscillations
implicitly take negative
gradient steps on the sharpness pushing
the sharpness down. These two things are coupled.
And if you want to analyze gradient descent, you go and analyze
that coupling.
Okay. Out for time. Oh, wow.
I have more time than I was expecting.
We,
so this was full batch grading
descent. But,
similar behavior has been shown for other
optimizers in the full batch setting.
Including Adam, for example,
if you wanna see the next step is to
analyze these dynamics.
And if you're curious about that,
we have this paper
understanding optimization in deep learning with
central flows. Which we
we wrote last year
And, I recommend the blog
post version of that.
We've got some animations there.
And finally, this was all
talking about full batch gradient
descent, which is not realistic,
but this is a special case
of a more general thing
holds for SGD.
And we're working on that currently, and we'll
put out a paper on that soon, hopefully.
Okay. So so what?
How does this suggest a better algorithm?
So that's a
some people's reaction. So in response, I would
say that's not our immediate goal.
Our our our thinking is that
practical algorithm design in deep learning
is not currently bottlenecked on
people working to apply
known principles, rather the barriers
that are principles that we don't know.
And that's the bottleneck.
And so we think the reason why we've been working
on this direction is that we think that the way
to maximize our long term impact on
practice to
focus now on understanding the foundations
so that later, we
or others can apply that understanding
to make practical algorithms that work effectively.
So maybe someone will put this theory to good use
next month, or maybe it will take a
long time. Either way, we
have faith that eventually, a
true understanding will yield practical
gains.
And perhaps big ones.
So if I could make a,
broader point about the field,
I I I I feel like most people in ML would say
that the platonic ideal of an ML paper
goes something like, oh, first you identify
some insight,
then you formalize that insight into a theorem,
and then you leverage that that insight
and that theorem to obtain
a new a new algorithm. That gets you
know, it's is the bold figure in the table.
That's sort of the Platonic ideal of a machine
learning paper. And
when I see a paper like that,
like a lot of the time my reaction is like,
like I I think to myself
like,
either like the theory is sort of like
exaggerated, or the experiments are exaggerated,
or both are exaggerated.
So I think that the field of ML I
don't think it's currently possible in most
cases to design
principled algorithms
that really work well in practice. The problem
is we just don't yet know what the principles are.
I think that the field sort of has this collective
action problem, so to speak, where
like, the official standard that everybody
holds themselves to is not
really attainable. In practice.
Like it's not really because we don't know what the principles
are, you can't really have a
work where you
you know, theorem
plus like like plus soda equals
theorem plus algorithm equals soda.
And so I would say that it's better to sort of
do something more modest in scope but but
do it well, than
to try to do too much.
And so, I think that, like,
the field would be a lot healthier if
there were less of an insistence on for
example, theorems instead we
should focus on understanding
and then the rigor will arrive gradually
over time. And similarly,
I think it's too ambitious to focus
every paper on trying to you
know, develop a state of VR
algorithm, we should instead focus on understanding
with the faith that true understanding will improve
the practice. In the course of time.
Finally, I wanna highlight
a great paper
that, Jamie Simon, Dan Dan Coonan,
and others have
put out
recently. I also help with this.
Called like there will be a scientific theory of deep learning.
Just containing some
promising directions
in this area. And you
should also check out this website, learningmechanics.pub,
which is gonna be a
it's gonna have, blog posts
on, topics in the theory of deep learning. So I
just wanted to call that
okay. Thanks.
And all the questions.
Thank you, Jeremy. That was, fantastic. So
if you have questions, you can go
to this mic at the front, or
you can also just raise your hand. And
then I will come to you with the mic.
So maybe to get started, Jeremy, I'm
sure you have some thoughts on
what kind of loss landscapes would drive the
would lead the gradient descent to drive sharpness
up because of course for quadratic objectives,
this doesn't happen. So, like Yeah. So that's one of the big
remaining like one of the big open
questions like, why does this
why does the sharpness tend to want to go up?
I mean, I think the heuristic
answer that a lot of people have is that
sharpness is something is correlated with something like complexity,
and so gradient descent is trying to
make the function more complex. As
it fits the dataset.
But that's just a hand waving notion.
So I I think it's still, open
problem.
Cool. Thanks. Yes, please.
Yeah. Thanks for the nice talk. I can hear
me from here? Yeah. Cool.
I have, like, kind of a simplistic takeaway, and I'm
wondering if you can disabuse me of it.
It seems like the when you're
in the weight space that
induces oscillations, well, as you've said, it's unstable.
And so I think, well, that kind of explains itself
a way that it's it's unstable, so you would
leave that region. But
why don't I just say something more nuanced? But I'm wondering
I can just kind of keep that in mind. But
you leave the region, but then why should something why shouldn't you just blow
up?
Why should you leave the region to a region where the
sharpness is lower rather than the region where it's higher? Yeah.
I guess just in the sense that you, like,
leave anywhere that's unstable. And then
the question is, like,
how common are unstable for
stable regions? But the the key point
is that, like,
I'm not saying that I'm saying when you look at this
third order expansion, it's not that like,
okay. Let me sorry. Let me go back.
I don't think I did this very well. The
So suppose we were,
suppose we're at this point. So go back to here.
Like, the things don't look so good.
Oh,
yeah. We've started to blow up.
Things don't look very good.
Let's say you wanted to fix the issue
manually. Right? So the what is the issue? The issue is
that the sharpness is too high.
So the most natural way to
fix the problem like, the sharpness
is is high enough that, like, locally,
like on our local quadratic model, we're
gonna blow up. And so, the
most natural way to fix the problem would be
okay, if the sharpness is too high, Let's move to
a region where the sharpness
It it automatically
picks up that grade that that grading of sharpness
term. Yeah. That was the third order of Heather.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I'm not Yeah. So I'm
not saying that the third order term is like
empirically something that we observe to be
aligned, like, aligned with the negative gradient, the sharpness.
I'm saying it is the it is the negative gradient
of the sharpness. So it always gives us
like the the stabilizing effect that we need.
So I guess I should take away from that. There's, like, something
even more precise than my intuition.
So Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Thanks for
that.
Thanks. Do we have, more questions?
Yes.
Yeah. Thank you for your talk. When I
see the loss like that, when the loss explodes
Yeah. I
Mhmm. And why the loss returns to the
same low loss region? Why model recovers
after the blow up? Yeah. Great question.
So it's because we were just bad along one direction.
Like, the loss was only high because
we were, we
were blowing up along this one particular direction,
the top eigenvector direction.
And so once we once the
curvature in that direction shrinks and you
you contract it getting along that direction, like, you you gain
back all the progress that you had apparently
lost. So it was like let me put it another way,
like, even when the loss was so
high, like the loss is high here now, if you
look at the average between like two consecutive
you take two consecutive iterates and you look at the
midpoint between them, the loss there is like not
bad. Like the spike only does
that make sense? Like if you were to pair average successive
iterates, that trajectory doesn't have a big
spike. Like, you're
only getting the spike because you're doing
it's literally just because you're doing like
this along one direction. How you should think
of things. You're good in all the other directions, but you're
doing this along one direction. Okay.
Okay. Yeah. Thank you.
Hi. Thank you very much for your talk.
Looks to me that this oscillation
is making you climb up the your local
convex region. Right? Yeah. Your
optimization space might be very regular.
This might be helping you to reach other
convex regions that have better local minimals.
It's a good Yeah. It's a good question. So
originally, like, that
was how like,
that seemed like to be a reasonable way to think think
of things. Our latest understanding is
that it's it's not good to think of things as like
transiting between it's it's not like gradients and
it's transiting transiting between like distinct,
like, discrete regions. Mhmm. Like,
instead like, what we what we argue in this
this sort of what we show in this, like,
more recent paper is that
this whole time, when it's at the
edge of stability, it's effectively
following this
this other differential equation. So it it doesn't
follow, like ordinarily, gradient descent follows the
gradient flow, but when it's at edge stability, it follows
like a different differential equation.
But so everything I I don't think of
like, the like, the oscillations mostly cancel
out. And there's this like smooth underlying picture.
I see. I Yeah. I don't think of it as distinct
regions, even though that is a natural way to think about it.
And would it be possible to map these,
convex regions and check if you
are actually jumping between them? Or
just staying the same. It's not like
I I don't know the answer. Yeah. I don't think it's
Yeah. I don't think of it as being jumping between
like, let me okay. Let me go back to this picture.
Oh,
Like, if if you go back to this
picture, like, what,
we go you see where we go out of the stable set, and
we get back in. Mhmm. You could
have affected it's basically doing the same thing as just
going to the border of stable set and then just staying there.
So, like, the that's, like, the big picture takeaway.
That, like, you should think of Grey Newsom as like moving
to the border of this table set.
And then implicitly, it's
projecting out the components of the gradient
that would bring us out of the stable set.
I I didn't get to that in this talk, but that's the
the right big picture takeaway. Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.
Yes. Maybe one more question. This last
picture got me thinking like,
if the stable
vision is pretty wide, but why we always
follow the one
really narrow reach region of that
stable? Region. And you think
it's
get some, similarity
with the platonic manifolds?
Like, that all basically models
if they trained long enough arrive to a similar
minimum. I
don't think
I don't think there's a Could you repeat So the
second half of the question I don't think there's a connection,
but I I haven't looked into it.
The first half of could you
clarify the first first part of the question again?
Yeah. So
this picture got me thinking that if
we always follow the just the edge of the stable
region Mhmm. We basically not
exploring all of the different possibilities
in the white space. Yeah. Good question.
But it's the the landscape is so overparameterized
that there are like good
Well, okay. If the learning rate is too
high, you can construct you can
definitely construct tasks where the learning rate is
so high enough that you can't even solve the
problem within the stable region. And you can't
get zero error. Is your
loss. That
is a possibility, but it's not it doesn't happen.
Most you can definitely construct examples where that
holds, but in practice,
this table region contains like
zero loss solutions. Just because there's the weight
space is I the big hand wavy justifications
of the weight space is so high dimensional
that you can it's like overparameters that
you can find a good solution even in there.
Alright. Makes sense. Thanks.
Okay. Let's thank Jeremy again for a great
talk.
Our next speaker is, Julian
Campe. Julia is a
silver professor of computer
science, mathematics, and data science
at, New York University. And she's currently
on leave at Meta Fair in Paris,
where she's a senior scientist and
director of the foundations of
reasoning team. And Julia
is known for very high quality
contributions to adversarial robustness,
model collapse and journey models, and
more recently reasoning in LLMs.
And she also had previous
lives in quantity finance at Renaissance,
and in, quantum computing and
information. And
we're, very excited to have a have
her here. And let's welcome her with a round of applause.
Yes. Hi. Can you hear me? Is it good?
So thank you for the organizers for
getting us to this wonderful location.
It's a real pleasure to be here in this workshop.
What I want to talk about today is, so
switching a bit, topics,
We're going to speak about
LLM reasoning, and trying
to understand some phenomena
that we are have all heard about. My
talk will basically be based on
let me see if I can get this better. Will be
based on two papers
One spearheaded by my student,
Nikos,
there on the top row, with Iran and
Karen, And another one
that was done at Meta, with
fantastic intern, Shobita.
And colleagues at Meta.
So, let me give you a little
bit of, you know, brief history of LLMs,
and we're gonna start right, in 2020
or slightly pre 2020.
Maybe you recall we had GPT two,
and the paradigm that emerged at the time
was let's pretrain this LLM,
and then let's fine tune it to
wherever we want it to go. You
know, new summarization or
something else. That was the paradigm.
And then around 2020,
these are all kind of empirics, right, that appeared.
People realized that these
pre trained next token prediction, pre trained LLMs
are fantastic in context learn
learners. There was a whole flurry
of the community trying to understand what's
happening in context, beautiful work
was done also theoretically to
understand what is the mechanism behind this in context
learning. And then, in 2022,
I would say, this
one in one of these papers, let's think step by step.
There was this new revolution where
when you tell the LLM, you just think
a bit, suddenly it became a much better
performer and also, in particular, a much
better reasoner. Right? And, again, there
is a lot to understand here. And for our community,
to kind of try to isolate the mechanism
of what's happening. So, this is pre history.
And then, about a
year and a bit ago,
we had the appearance of these so called reasoning
models, I think the first one maybe
that we can pin down is o one, followed
very quickly by Deepseak and Kimmy,
where, there was a new kind
of training or post training paradigm
which is now called RLBF,
reinforcement learning with verifiable
rewards. Which led to fantastic,
you know, progress in coding and
math and all these, verifiable
domains, also in science, basic
So, this is interesting because there's a lot to understand
here. And just, stepping
forward because people keep asking me what's now,
think what most of us observe now is yet
another phase transition where we
start to have several
agents, API access to
powerful foundation models, that we make interact.
Right? And, there's fantastic new territory
scientifically to understand there
is now, instead of in weights
RL, there's maybe in context RL or
in skill learning, all these new things
are happening, and I'll try to allude to them. But,
let me focus on stuff
that happened about a year ago and what
what we try to understand. Okay.
So, reinforcement learning for LLM
post training, we already had
RLHF where we kind of you
know, had had responses of the
LLM, and then we waited them, we had them annotated,
one better, one worse, and we did reinforcement
learning. And the kind of reasoning revolution,
that started about a year ago, a little more,
was to do this, you know, open AI,
as I said, deep sea and Kimmy.
Was to do several rollouts, several
thinking traces of the LLM, and
then, you know, have some sort of group average
of the reward and reinforce these thinking
traces. And this,
mechanism, which is which
was called group relative policy optimization
and about 500 versions of
it later. I mean, maybe not 500, but many,
the paradigm was basically that, as
I said, you have these rollouts. Right? A
group of multiple chain
of thought outputs, say 16,
Right? And then, you have a verifier that checks
after this long chain of thought the output is
and whether it's correct or wrong. And then, the
verifier gives a reward, which is often binary.
And then some sort of average is computed, and then
everything better than the average
gets rewarded, and everything worse. Than
the average gets penalized. And this is kind
of put back into the loss And
restarted. Right? So, this is a this is
the the mechanism And, what
people observed is, that
during that ROVF training,
the chain of thought lengths would increase. Right? And
you've probably all seen these famous curves
of how how it goes. Up and then
also, you know, test time, compute increases,
of course, because then the answers have a long
chain of thought. And this is all very interesting,
but do we understand it and where is it coming from?
Right? So this is what we wanted to understand. What does
this RLVF actually do? I mean, many
people wanted to understand it, but here, I'm gonna
present one way to isolate isolate this
mechanism. So,
and then also the question that was then, you
know, being it's still being discussed in the community
is, do we actually learn something, or are
we just retrieving something that's in the training
data hidden somewhere? Right? So that's the
question. And I'm you know, there's a quote
by Bubeck in one of the interviews
he gave where he says,
the intelligent already intelligence already exists
in the pre trained model,
it's all about extracting it. And I'm
putting it there slightly provocatively because
I actually don't believe this is fully true,
but there is some truth to this. I think.
And that's what our role does. So let's try to understand
this a little better. But before
we do, there is this other question
which, or maybe it's complementary or similar.
There were these observations, by many
papers, including one of ours,
where we compare the model before it
was trained with this RLBF procedure
and we we we we look at pass
at k pass at higher k rates.
So, we ask the model to do a
128 rollouts And if there's one correct
one, then we say pass it k as one safe.
Instance. And we compare this high
pass it k rates with then the post
trained RLBF model. When you look at
these number of samples here,
you can actually see in some experiments,
and again, this this is still being debated. Sometimes
it's true. Sometimes it's less true. But you
can see that, basically, the RL
model, the RLVF model, tends to
become sometimes even worse than the base
model at pass at higher k. So then,
people just say, you know, RLVF
does nothing but bring the pass at k.
To the pass at one. But then it becomes
less diverse and so on and so forth. Right?
So this is also observations
people have made.
And, there's another paper I like that
also appeared about a year ago,
by I think, people at Harvard.
And also I think mostly
people at Harvard. Where they did just
a controlled study because it's very hard to study
this we don't have any understanding
of what the pretraining data set looks like.
Right? I mean, we don't know mean, we do know it's the
Internet, but we don't know how the data is curated
in the foundation models. They did
a study where they just retrained a model from
scratch, pretrained it, had a very
careful look at the pre training data sets.
And what they observed is,
let's see. In particular, what they
observe is that our
algorithms consistently converge towards
a dominant output distribution distribution amplifying
patterns in the pre training data. Right?
So, they observe it by having different flavors of
pre training data, different formatings,
etcetera, and they see that RL picks up one
of them. For math or whatever.
We wanted to understand this a little better.
What that means. Right? And so, our
hypothesis here was that
in the pre training data, you
will have a lot of short
data in the sense that there is a question and an answer,
something like this. Then occasionally, you have
very high quality data where
you have a question, then a long
explanation, deliberation, thinking trace,
then an answer. Right?
And, so
what we did in the study is we assumed that when
you have a long pattern, then you
can generalize pretty well from it.
If you know how to think. You have a short
pattern, just question answer, you
cannot quite, generalize because it's
it doesn't reveal the thinking we are
making this assumption that that's how the pre training
data looks like then we
want to understand what RLVF or RL,
gRPO, etcetera, does
to this. So, particular, we are asking
why is it difficult for a model
to generalize if you just do pretraining
or just do SFT, next talk and prediction,
And what is this thing that RLBF does or
our reinforcement learning in general to
suddenly get this knowledge out. Right? And
why why do the thinking traces then get longer?
Right? So, this this was the question we asked.
And so we we wanted to isolate this mechanism
and we started with a very controlled
experiment And we were lucky that this experiment
was devised in such a way that in a slightly
simplest setting, we could actually prove everything.
We have like a full theory, that
matches these experiments. Because they
are actually somewhat analyzable. But
first, let's let's describe the experiments.
So we modeled the pre training data
with a parity problem. Parity,
you know, zero one and then the
the sum is even or odd. Basically.
XOR of or if you wish XOR of the training
bits. So we have inputs
our training bits, bits, sorry, bit strings.
And then in the training data, we have a mixture
Either we have, long demonstrations,
where we have these bits of input, and
then we have these partial parities. You see
this there on the bottom line of this blue yellow
red. So, we have the blue input, It's
a string of zero ones.
And then the yellow bits there are
partial parities, so the parity of the first bit,
the parity of the first and the second bit, the first second
third, and so on. Is how you would compute
parity probably. Right? You would go along the
chain, compute the partial parities. I mean,
how else can you do it? Right? And then, the red is the
output bit. So what we what we'll
have is training a training mixture
for a small transformer which
is a lot of these short answer
parities and
a a few, a fraction, which we call
p of chain of thought, p code,
of these long demonstrations. And
what you need to know about parity is usually one, you know, in
theoretical computer science, it's always used
as prototypical hard problem. It's hard.
Parity is not so easy. To
do, you know. Whereas, if you have this
long chain of thought, and you just follow
it along and you reason this way, then
it becomes easy. Right? So, this is
our training mix. So, we use this dataset that
has a lot of these short demonstrations,
and some of these longer demonstrations
And, our hypothesis is that this is basically
mimicking the Internet we have some
step of step reasoning step by step reasoning
examples but there there's like, they are drowned
in this sea of very short answers.
And the noise and so on and so forth. Right?
So just we did this experiment. We ran a small transformer
on it. And what we observed is that, and we
have a next token prediction, I should say. So
what we observed is indeed when the transformer
kind of starts mimicking the dataset
it's trained on. So, if there is, for instance,
20% long demonstrations,
and 80% short, then
the transformer will also at the end of
training output, 20% long
stuff and 80% short
stuff. So, it remains length calibrated.
If you just do SFT next
token prediction, pretraining. We saw it
in experiments we could prove this also
theoretically with a with a simplified
model. With a, you know, with an ensemble
of linear
transformers. So,
and on the other hand, when it got a long one,
so in the 20% of cases where it had a long
one, it very quickly learned
to generalize. So it generalized
meaning to unknown sequences. Right?
So, in the test set, we had sequences
of bits that they didn't see that the transformer
didn't see in. And, pre training, And,
whenever it decided to output a long answer,
it was very quickly learning to be correct.
But for the short answers, it just, you
know, it would have take I mean, it just didn't work.
Right? It just was hard a hard problem to
learn. So, as a result,
when you look, when we did the analysis then,
we had like, on the
left side, you see this accuracy for
various mixtures of this
long demonstrations in the data set.
So if there's enough long demonstrations, in fact, there
was a threshold at one third,
when you have more than a third of good demonstration
long demonstrations, and then
you do, and then you look at the accuracy, see
how quickly it learns to
predict the right answer when it answers
with a long demonstration,
which will happen, you know, in a good
number of cases. And when you do greedy decoding,
for instance, which is on the, right
side, then there's this threshold of one third.
Of the mixture of the pretraining data
before, if you if you have less than this,
good demonstrations you just have no
accuracy. Because in the greedy case,
will just always output the short ones.
Because it remains length calibrated. So if it doesn't
have a choice, a randomness, will always
do the short demonstrations, won't learn anything.
Right? It will only guess randomly 50%.
But, once you have more than a third,
it will learn to output, with higher
probability, long demonstrations where it quickly
learns. Right? So, all this we observed.
And I'm not gonna bore you with the theory,
but all this we could literally prove, including
the one third, for our
linear transformer with the frozen
layer, basically. So so that was nice.
So that made us understand why SFT
fails, but that was not what we wanted
to understand. We wanted to understand what happens with RL.
And so now what we did is after we've
trooped pre trained this transformer,
we now did what RL does. So, good
answer, we would reinforce it.
We would say, you know, we would give it a positive
reward, whenever there was a wrong
answer, we would give it a negative reward. So what
happens is whenever it sees a
long demonstration, the answer will be correct. Right? Because
we had pre trained it. So, the long
ones would be picked for, like,
being positively rewarded all the
time. And for the short ones, only half
of them would be correct, So there would
be much less of them picked, only half of
So, at every step of this And then we would
re retrain the model. Right?
I mean, then we would basically reinforce
this thing and keep going. So, as a
result, we kind of up sample the long ones
because they get rewarded much higher
probability, namely one, basically. And
And as a result, after logarithmically
few rounds in the fraction in the lengths, I mean,
in one over the fraction,
of the long ones, we get
to perfect accuracy and also the length
of the chain of thought, of course, increases because
it was start outputting only the long chain of
thought. And we can see all this here.
So, here is this training we
have very few long demonstrations, like, say, 20%
or 2% or 5%. And we
see how we train, and then we switch. So we train
SFT and we get to this 50%
but no more because, you know, under greedy
decoding, it will just output short
things. And then, at some point, we'd
stop and do this RL training. And
you see how immediately the accuracy
just jumps up to
nearly a 100%. Right?
We RLBF.
Procedure, which is exactly what our theory says.
And the length of the chain of thought
would increase after we do this, and it takes
very few rounds. So, all this we saw in
the experiments, in the theory, it was
very rewarding for us because basically, we
started with the hypothesis that there is
some good stuff in the pretraining data, lots
of not so good stuff, here's the mechanism
by which RL actually you
know, zooms into what happens in the
training data. So, here is
the length increase, I guess. We we see some sort
of, heat map of the length. But,
this is all just to reinforce the message that with this parity
example, we could explain what's happening
in RL. And let me,
now summarize the mechanism again. So, during pretraining,
what happens is the model quickly learns from
the long stuff. But it doesn't increase the
long stuff. So, when it sees, when it decides to output
a long chain of thought, knows how to generalize.
Right? But, when it decides
to output a short chain of sort, it's too hard
to learn disparity. It fails to learn.
And because it remains length calibrated,
it will be wrong a lot of the time if
there's very few good samples in the training data.
Right? And then, during
post training, this RLBF or
we we analyze the star algorithm where we just
picked good, you know, positive reward
samples and did some SFT on those and iterated
this. So, because RL
rewards correctness of
you know,
reward weighted correctness, the the
it effectively up samples the long chain
of sorts samples of the correct stuff from which
it can learn. And shifts the model policy
this way. Right? And
then, because this goes so fast, this,
you know, this up boot bootstrapping
quickly, you can do the calculation, it's really
very fast at logarithm
one of a P code. Right? So, r l
is highly effective to mine and capitalize
on rare, high quality examples.
Which, you know, which was kind of a wisdom
that people already kept repeating, but we were pleased
to see this here, And also
the long chain of thought, it's not because,
language model needs a scratch pad or anything.
It's in this case, it really comes from the optimization
pressure of this
learning procedure. Alright.
And then, because we also wanted
the paper to have some relevance, we repeated
this in the wild. So, we actually took
pre trained LLMs. I think in
this case, it was some llama
model. What is it? LLAMA three b. And we
did this with GSM. It came with the math data set.
We repeated this study. So, either we did the
GSMAK with a mixture of no
chain of thought and full chain of thought,
and we did SFT, and then we did RL, exactly
like with the parity, and we see exactly the same
phenomenon. Right? So it doesn't learn very much, and the moment
we stop and switch to RL, the learning
goes up. Like crazy in logarithmic in many
steps. So exactly the same
mechanism for pretrained models. So
so we were happy that this framework
explains something. Alright.
Let me switch quickly to a second,
problem. So, with ROI, as we
saw, with RLBF, what happens is
that you during learning, you give
it like 16 chances output of chain
of thought, and then you'll amplify the
correct answer and penalize the wrong answer.
What if the problems are so hard
that there is no correct answer in the beginning?
Right? So hard with this procedure, where you
need something to I mean, you need a signal, you
need at least one of them to be correct.
Kind of hopeless for hard problems when nothing
is correct. Right? I mean, obviously, because because, you
need you need to amplify something.
So, hard problems cannot be learned,
with ROVF unless you try very, very long
time and then randomly some correct answer happens
and then you amplify this. Right?
So, and and as we said, these
current r l recipes also primarily
preserve the base model solution coverage. So,
it's really kind of a bit doomed with
hard problems, and what people have been doing
for a long time Oh, let me not
people have been doing for a long time is they try to design
curricula. Right? I mean, for
these math problems, very hard,
Remember, there was first college math was solved with GSMAK,
and then high school math, right, with the math
data set. And then the IMO, that's only
last year, remember? I mean, IMO, Putnam,
all these are happening, but it's, there's no coincidence
that it goes step by step, so to
speak. So there's lots of curriculum
design going on, but it's often handcrafted.
Right? So, we try to give it easy problems,
medium problems, hard problems. But
what if we don't actually know what is easy,
medium, and hard? Like, I ask you to solve the Riemann
hypothesis, come tell me what's the easiest I mean,
what are the stepping stones? We don't know. Right? So
if we were ambitious. So how do we
automate this curriculum learning
and so this is our paper at the edge of learnability.
Edge of learnability means you can't learn
it, but then if you're clever, you can learn it. Right? So, we have this
plateau, we have no training signal.
What do we do? Our LDF will just wander around
and not find anything.
So, we need this curriculum and it's often done
curated data, filter existing data,
all these handcrafted ways, but it's
either it's not principled or it doesn't
work or it has its problems. Right?
So the idea here is maybe the LLM
from its huge pretraining set,
already kind of knows or has enough easy
problems Right? Riemann hypothesis.
It has read all the papers on the archive.
Maybe there is a curriculum of stepping stone math
results to the Riemann hypothesis We just don't know
it. I mean, I'm being ambitious here. Okay.
So, let the LLM itself decide
what is its curriculum. This is the idea of
the self play and self improvement. And
so, we designed one such procedure. This
is this is an experimental result, and we're
now having some theory around it. But,
this is just to was like kind of, can we
isolate this and make this work? Right? So,
what we did is we took the LLM, we split
it into two copies, a teacher and a student.
The teacher is the one who's supposed to tell
the problems, The student is the one who's
supposed to learn a bit on the problems,
and the teacher is rewarded for the improvement
of the student. Compared to
a student that didn't have a teacher. Right? So, relative
improvement. So, this was our idea. It's a simple
idea. Was just a bit hard to make it work
because you had an outer loop for the teacher and inner
loop for the student, and we're not the
first one to have these self improvement frameworks.
There was lots of work in particular to find
some sort of intrinsic student reward.
The teacher would be rewarded for giving
a hard question or kind of
right question where half of the rollouts would
be right of the students, half of them were wrong. So there's
lots of intrinsic reward work.
And I'll get back to this too. And
the other thing is that this was inspired by works,
in in in South play, an asset self play.
For the last ten years, people have
thought about this also in exploring mazes,
and in robotics, and there were these papers
by OpenAI in 2021,
in particular, that used this kind of idea of
a teacher student setup to,
improve robotic kind of
motion and so on. Right? So, this
is not, completely unprecedented.
So here's what we did. Right? To come back to this, we have
this teacher. The teacher will give
question answer pairs. We just ask
the teacher to produce them. They'll be given
to a student in batches. The student
does a little bit of ROVF on them.
And then we evaluate the student on this really,
really hard data set that we can't
solve, but would like to solve, and see if there's
any improvement. And if there is some improvement,
the teacher gets a reward. The teacher also does
RLBF, so teacher does this also in
in groups. And this is the mechanism
we, implemented. Right?
So, here is, the notebook
LLM version of the
same thing. So we did this by
level optimization. Which, you
know, also has lots of precedent.
And, after doing all this, it worked.
That's a short message. And it worked.
These graphs take my word for it, I'm not gonna
explain all these lines, but the blue line is
the baseline, and the top lines, they are not
the dotted line, but the other red lines there,
is how our various versions of this
algorithm actually help and and the
x axis is pass at k, for
various k in this. Yes. I I
I'll I'll So, it
worked. It's nice. And it worked even
out of domain. So, we trained
curriculum, in one setting
for math, and then we had it on Olympiad
bench and still the stepping stone
curriculum helped. Right? So so this is nice.
And I want to also come back to this intrinsic
reward As I said, there
are several works that already tried this,
with having rewards that are not grounded. Not
like, how much do you really improve on
the real data set that you care about, but more like,
is the question hard enough that the student has to think
a bit, but not too much? And, these
things tend to work a little bit in the beginning and then a
reward hacking hack sets in. I mean, it's fantastic.
We run these things It's absolutely
amazing what kind of re The the LLM
is so creative to hack the rewards. It's
unbelievable. So had a lot of fun seeing
this, and this is also what people observe. Right? So one
lesson here is why don't do the intrinsic
rewards not work so well, when
you when you I mean, there's lots here to explore
also with more, targeted experiments.
Anyway, and one thing, one fun
thing we learned was these stepping
stone questions that the teacher produced, it
actually didn't it didn't matter so much whether they
were correct. They were often wrong, as in, like, the
answer was wrong. It was like gave, like,
what did it give five over nine when it's supposed to
be don't know what I mean, you can see here.
So it was more often important
to have a correct chain of reasoning rather
than have the correct answers. That was fun.
We saw that. And now I'm coming to my last
thirty five seconds of, view
to the future. So, I gave you all this
pre history of LLMs, and now we are in this
agent self improvement, autonomous AI.
And models starting to teach themselves
era. And, I think
what's now interesting to understand for our community
is basically in these multi
agent workflows where we do everything in harness,
so you have all these new papers
appearing, right, where you don't do RL and wait
anymore. You do it RL in harness, in skill.
You have to meta learning with
writing to the skills, the cloud writing
to the skills, etcetera. There's a lot of
interesting new questions appearing here. Right? Because we can
also now enforce diversity by having different agents having
different prompts and so on and so forth. So
there's lots to understand. In these kind
of You can also have it We are working on these teacher
student setups now for these
kind of agentic frameworks. And, you know, we It's
it's fantastic. And if there are several agents are
better than one agent, all that stuff. But
I think the big question that remains here is,
whether we can whether LLMs
or models can
actually bootstrap themselves out of the
best human. Right? So so far, we were in an
age where we had data that was annotated
by humans. Written by humans,
and now it's written, you know, now it's
only annotated by the best humans. I mean, if you don't
have PhD, don't even work as an annotator.
Guess, that's what I hear from on Tropic. Right? Not not
Nobel Prize, that's like what they have as
their annotators now. So, clearly,
we are reaching level
where the best human is passer.
Right? I mean, there's very little that the,
human can still annotate. I mean, I'm exaggerating
a little bit. Another question is, can the model
transcend this? And I think you talk to people
on the West Coast, they will say, oh, we're already there.
I'm a little more skeptical.
But we have, we have evidence. Right? Like, look at AlphaGo. All
this self improvement, self,
you know, the self play loops,
it made it a Go player that is clearly way
better than a human. All these games.
Right? For code, let's face it. I mean, yes,
there are still, hiccups, but
it's transcended, but code is very
verifiable and constrained. Math, I don't know if you
mathematicians, they say never, it will never fall.
I think math will fall also, and some point
very soon with these loops, but where's the
boundary? Where is there a boundary? Right? What is
it about self play that will make it transcend
we don't have any more annotation because the human
has been left behind? Right? So I think these questions
are very interesting to understand. And with
this, because I'm already way over time,
I'm stopping and you very much.
We have time for one question.
Further questions can be referred to the
coffee break. So if you have one
question, just raise your hand or
walk to the mic.
Okay.
Thanks for the great talk. So,
yeah, it's really interesting to to,
to to see the contrast between your approach and
Jeremy's approach. And so I I I have a question,
that that that that comes more from,
from from this sort of, like, first principles predictive
science type of thing. Like, I tend to shy
away from studying things like
reasoning self by curriculum, because I kinda feel like I just don't
know how to do good science of this.
Because, like, for, you know, for me, I feel like
if I can't put the dots on theory lines or something,
then I then I just don't know how to trust what I'm doing. So like,
how do you think about going about doing this and
and and, like, doing science that tells you things
that you trust and can build on and all this? Like Yeah. No.
I think it's an excellent question. You, Jamie.
Right? I mean, I think of this as first being
a sorry. An experimental physicist and then
a theoretical physicist in some ways. Right? So
I think first, the art is to
isolate certain mechanism where you
can just have a very simple experiment, like
we had with the parity, or, you know, many
others, to isolate the phenomenon. I think
that's that's number one and that's what makes
reasoning less scary, I think. You just find
the thing where it still reasons and you can actually
understand the data, etcetera. And then you can sit, I think
once you've isolated these mechanisms,
and make them smaller, think then you can
do the theory, which we did in this by the way, Nikos is here
on this first paper, you can ask him question
later. But then you can,
then you can build a theory, I think.
So you have to just first make it less
daunting and then you can attack it. Think.
I don't know. That helps, but yeah.
Great answer. Let's sing Julia again.
And our last speaker for this,
first morning session, is
David Bao. David is an assistant professor
of computer science at Northeastern University.
And David David has been a leading
figure in, AI interpretability
for a long time now, and he's been doing mechanistic
interpretability before the
term was coined. And recently,
it's been also now
applying interpretability to
model strain on scientific tasks. And
trying to extract scientific knowledge from
these models, which find very exciting.
He's going to tell us about. And something
that you might also not know about David is that he's
the author of a very popular
numerical linear algebra. Textbook.
Escape and then start again.
Yeah. It was showing up. Oh, it was showing?
I think it's good.
It's like Okay.
Very good. Thank you, David. Let's, let's Thank you very
much. Warm. I I love I
love that progression of talks
here and Julia Sock in her last notes that
you know, we're clearly in this
this this shifting, this very
quickly shifting field in 2026
where, we are now starting to learn how
to train these models.
To to really
see superhuman capabilities I think
that it'll be more and more routine. For
us to be confronting AI models
that we're using in daily life that,
seem to know things. That
we don't know. That maybe no
human knows, and it leaves us with this question,
which is sort of the theme of my talk.
Where does that leave us? As
people, as scientists and what can we do about it?
So what I'm gonna share with you today is a little bit
of how to read the science back out of
deep learning. I think this is an
immature field, but I'll show you a few of the steps
that we're trying to take to to do this in
one of the domains.
But, but it's a little bit of a shift
here for a different topic. So I want to calibrate
by asking people
who's familiar with this type of
experiment? So it's a warm up question.
Who who knows what a patching experiment
is? What what the what the heck
is a patching experiment? It's
it's an odd
technique. It's an an empirical experimental
technique that's used in my community, but it
it isn't that widespread. So, let me just give
you this background because it's a tool
that is central to a bunch of the
methods in the talk. So in a
patching experiment, it's so it's
it's it's an experiment that you can do with an
artificial neural network which is
like the neuroscientist's dream. It's
like what if you could give a
person like a brain transplant to figure
out how their brain works? Right?
Obviously, you can't do that with a person. But
with a neural network, what you can do is
you can run two
neural networks either slightly different
neural networks or maybe two identical
neural networks in slightly different context
you know, working on slightly different problems. And then,
you can transplant
a neural state from one
of the runs to the other
run, as a way of
asking us as a way of asking, you know,
in a very, very focused way
What is being represented in
that transplanted neural state? Like if
you hypothesize that what that neural
state has is maybe it's
thinking about the number 14,
then you can run the model
in a different way where you think maybe it's thinking
about the number 10 and you transplant
what you think is the encoding of 14 down
to the other one and see if
you change the behavior of the other model
to to behave as if it was thinking about 14.
Right? So like in this case,
you have some crazy story and
you ask okay, what's
what's what's the drink in the cup? And
it says tea, and then you have some
different story and it's some complicated logic and
it says what's
It's coffee and then you think, okay, I'll I'll transplant
one of the clues down from one run
to the other and we'll see
does it change? Does it change coffee to
something else? And once in a while,
if you bring over the so most of the time,
you bring over some state and these experiments
fail. Most of the time, your hypothesis
is wrong, you try to do a
little transplant patching experiment and it doesn't
change the output, but once in a while
you bring something over and
voila, right? You can switch coffee to tea,
It gets the model to do something different,
And and then you can get very surprising
results when doing this kind of thing. So here's
a result from a poster
from one of my students. That was
presented yesterday. Sorry, this
is in the wrong order, so I can't direct
you to talk to him at his poster. Because
that's in the past, but will be talking more
about this again tomorrow at the realign workshop.
So in this experiment,
you can patch a certain thing and
the original question
answers t where you're
patching from and you're patching to
a run where it said coffee, just like I
showed you. But if you patch
it different layers, instead
of it flipping from coffee to tea,
in this particular experiment, if you
switch to early layers, it's
it patches in
a way that switches the answer from coffee
to beer
and you can stare at this experiment for a little
bit. I'm not going to dwell on it because I don't
have time to go through this one today.
But I'll talk a little bit more about it tomorrow.
But this is this is one of
the really puzzling It's like
a little Sudoku puzzle. It's like a, you
know, it's figuring out like why does it
flip to beer this really interesting
exercise in untangling the logic
that's that the neural network has learned
inside and these patching experiments really
allow you to to
discover the non trivial algorithms that
are learned by by these
networks and, and so the
structure that I think this community
is studying in the abstract,
You guys you know, studying learning theory
and how complexity can be learned
in in different ways. What we
do is we look to see what
specific kinds of complex methods are
learned and what specific representations are learned
in and I think that there's quite a bit
of insight that you can get from looking at
these specifics. So I encourage you
to to see a little bit about what's going on in this
community. This
talk today, I'm gonna be
talking about
work by Kevin Liu
to unpack
eight AI protein folding models. And
so the reason this is
interesting is because it's exactly the situation
that Julia talked about You know,
there's a very expensive
and in the real world.
This is you know, this
in this example, people are trying to solve
breast cancer They know that there's a
a a
tumor factor that, is implicated
in causing breath breast cancer,
and they think maybe we can design a
drug that stops the cancer from progressing
if we can just find some
protein that binds to this and turns off
these receptors. Right? And so,
the way that you do this today
is you heuristically guess
many many thousands and thousands of possible
drugs and then you have to physically test
them to see, you know, do they fold to the right shape?
To bind, to the target that you're
trying to get? And it costs quite a
bit of money every time you do another batch
of these It's another
dollar experiment and and
the combinatorial space that you have to study
is so large. It's really prohibitive
to to develop a drug like this.
And this is just in the first stage of drug design.
So, but what's happened now is
the the models like
AlphaFold, there's open source ones, there's
ESM fold and so on.
That have advanced advanced the the
state of the art. They've really revolutionized
biology because
now you can get such accurate
protein folding predictions out of these AI
models that you get like a 10
to 100 times speed up. In
getting more accurate
folding predictions before you actually have to do
it in wet lab. And so that's there's
a vast savings and it's really
changed Oh, why is this going ahead?
Do I have timings on this? I might
have to turn this off?
Okay. So so, but then
it leaves it leaves to this question.
You've got this amazing AI,
that that you've trained, that
can that can solve this classic
scientific problem better than any of the
previous algorithms made by scientists.
But but it
it it leads it leads us to question of what does
it leave us humans and scientists
Is this science? If we've
trained some giant model
and it can do the science better than we can,
if we don't know how it works?
If we don't know what it does,
is this you know, is this science or
is this the end of science? And
so what I propose is that
actually one of the things that's important for
us to do is as we start to get
AI models that are superhuman
that we develop methods for getting the
knowledge back out of the models so that we can understand the
generalizable principles and
maintain our agency, maintain our knowledge,
and remain our you know retain
our role as scientists as going
forward. So let's let's do this exercise
in the protein folding models.
I'm gonna give you a little background on how protein
folding models work. I think it's interesting.
It gives you a little sense for the diversity of
different types of architectures out there that
you might want to study that are a little different
from the language models that are everywhere.
So in a protein photo model, the way it
works is you start with
a sequence of proteins, so a
sequence of aminos. There's 20
different amino acids, When you
chain them together, they they lose a couple of atoms
and we call them residuals. So
you see these letters e v q l, these
each one of them. Corresponds to
a residual and
and then the goal is going to be to go from
the sequence of residuals to a
three d shape. And the
all the state of the art protein folding models
do this in three steps. The first step,
is you train it
you train it on language model embedding.
Just a regular, transformer
to take one of these sequences out and then
turn it into a vector representation.
For for one one vector for
every residual. And then, the second
thing that happens is you put it through a folding trunk
This is another transformer it's
a specialized transformer with an unusual architecture
I'll talk about in a minute. That's
designed to help folding problems.
So it's a little different from a language model.
And it's driven by a pair
of representations. There's a sequence representation and
there's something called a pair wise representation,
which is like a two dimensional. It's a it's a
matrix representation instead of
a sequence representation. And then
after it goes through through
50 or so layers of folding trunk
computations, then it goes
through a final model called
the structure module which which
is a readout. It turns all these things into three
d shapes. It gives you
three-dimensional
locations for every atom. In the
in the protein. And,
then you get these beautiful three
d protein structure predictions out that you can do
chemistry with. With.
Okay. So, so that's that's the background
of what the architecture is. And it
and then it leads so now what
our question is, is well statistically,
these things are trained to do very
well, They do better than all the quantum simulations
that people have made in the past. Right?
How does it work? What does it do inside?
And so we don't have a complete
accounting for this. This this work is a
preliminary investigation of how the computation
is organized. But give
you a little sense for how you can make progress with
a question like this. So there's three
questions that we basically ask. One is
a localization question. There's all
these parts of the computation Can we
localize where different
parts of the computation are happening?
Right? Is is the problem just
it solved all monolithically or is it solved
step by step inside all these layers?
And and the typical experiment
formed to do this is the patching experiment
that I showed you before. So I'll show you a patching
experiment here. And then then then
the other questions are, okay, once
you see where the problem solved,
what concepts are being represented,
in this solution and can we directly
change those concepts and edit it and
verify we've got? Okay.
So what Kevin did here to start understanding
things is he said, you know, there's a lot
of different problems solved by the protein
folding models. But one of the problems is to
is to recognize when the proteins
fold and it's very
narrow a hairpin shape,
This very narrow u shape, so that's shown in purple
on the right. It's called a beta hairpin.
So this is is a place where in
the protein it goes out in a flat
sheet for several several base,
you know, for several residues and then makes
a 180 degree turn and then
that folds back on itself. Again. So
of like that purple shape. And so,
the models are very good at predicting
when this happens, and he wanted to understand,
you know, how they how they do that. They figure this
out? And so, he set up a very simple
patching experiment to do this, and
let me show you how this works. So,
his intuition or actually
it was based on some other experiments, but, you know,
his his his found that
the main work is done inside this
big middle model, the folding trunk.
But the folding trunk has two different representations
it's dealing with. It's dealing with
this sequence representation and this
funny pairwise representation. Representation
He had no idea where to start Should he
be looking at one of these halves? Or the
other half? How can you tell
So he set up a pair of patching
experiments one on the sequence
And what what he does is this. For
his patching experiments, he needs to
have two runs. He has a
run where the it's it's sort of
like the coffee and tea setup I I described to you
at the beginning. Is one run where
there's a a hairpin
being predicted And then, he has a
different run, where when the model is acting correctly,
there's no hairpin being predicted. It's it's
at it's at alpha helix. In the left hand side.
It's not it's not a long hairpin.
Right? So this
protein that this protein sequence he puts in on the
bottom doesn't have a hairpin.
But his question is, can
he find where the decision is inside
the model that causes it to
decide to have a hairpin? Can he patch some
concept in the middle of the model down
to the second run? So that when you
run it, it changes its mind and says, oh,
you know what? I think that there should be a hairpin here.
Right? So that that would that
would do it, like that would show him where this localized
decision is. And he
and then so I
some of this work is quite painstaking. Right? It
it took him many months
to figure out how to set it up and how to localize
this but eventually you got this critical
experiment working so he's this is these are his
slides. He's so proud of this.
Where he he ran this pair of experiments
and he found yes, there are two
domains where if you patch
a small number of vectors from one
run to the other, you can get the
hairpin to show up. And,
and the way that he does this is
he has thousands of
proteins without hairpins, he has thousands of proteins
with hairpins, and he patches from
the proteins that have the hairpins to
random proteins that don't have hairpins,
and and then he just measures
to see like how often patching it's specific
locations has the effect And so
the orange results
here correspond to
the sequence
the sequence result being patched.
And the green results here
correspond to the pairwise
representation being patched. And he
found that the sequence representation when you patch
it, it very early layers like this
first seven layers, of the folding trunk, then
you can fool the model into thinking oh,
we should have a hairpin. But
but if you try to do it with the
wise representation at the early layers, it doesn't do
anything. You have to patch
the pairwise representation way off at layer
30, in order to fool it into having a hairpin.
So you can see these very different roles
and and so this leads to his hypothesis
that there's two major phases
in how the protein folding model is working.
There's this early phase where he hypothesized
there's biochemical signatures that
you get that are local
from the the individual
residues and then it turns it into
a spatial prediction in the second phase.
Which you can intercept
in the pairwise representation in the later layers. And
so, okay. So now, what are the actual concepts
that it's that it's using? What's being
passed from this sequential
state to the pair wide state.
What goes from one to the other?
So, what what he
did is he said, okay. So
let let me let me zoom in to show you
what you mean by passing
from one to the other. So inside the folding trunk, you
have these two streams
of representations the sequence and the pairwise
representations. The pairwise representation if
you have it's it's an n squared representation. So if
you have a 100 residues
in your protein then the pairwise representation is
a 100 by 100 matrix. Right? So
it's it's a 10,000
you know, element. There's like 10,000
tokens. A way of thinking of And
and so, so when you
enter the folding trunk, this
pairwise representation is has has no
information about the protein. It's just initialized
with, positional embedding.
But then, as you go through the layers
of the folding trunk, it picks
up information from the sequence
representation through some
internal data flows
in inside. The neural network
like this. So there's a pair
to a sequence to pair
update, where it does an outer product
of of the
sequence representations to sort of give
you an update to the the pairwise
representation and and then there's a
paired sequence thing that gives you back
the other way. So it's just data mixing
technique. And the question is, you
know, what's actually being passed? So
so what he does is he asks
does the
you know, do basic biochemical
properties do
they get represented in one
of these sides or the other? So he starts
off by asking about
electrostatic charge So
there are aminos that
have very strong positive charge and
different aminos that have very
strong negative charge. And he says,
can you predict can you
read out from the sequence
side or the or the pair
wise side whether,
given amino is positive or
negative. And and the answer is
yes. You can. You can read it out basically
a 100% but
but what the interesting thing is
the information shows up in the pairwise
side at about layer seven.
The information is not there reliably.
For the first seven layers, but then but
then it's very strongly present in the side
after layer seven, which which corresponds
to this transition where
the causal experiment said
the sequential information is really important
up to layer seven. But then after layer
seven is not very important anymore,
So what this suggests is that layer seven
the this biochemical information
is passed over to the pair wise side of the representation
and and
and
and then proceeds on from there.
So,
okay. So, let me let me give you
then there's this sort of the second
form of the experiment you do Okay.
So let me let me back up and give you
the
I'm getting a little bit into the details of Kevin's
experiments. I'm using his slides here.
But let me back up and give you
a sense for what's
going on in this type of work.
There's basically two forms of experiments
you can ask. You can ask is
information present And
you can ask, is the information
actually used by the model?
And so in this kind of experiment that Kevin
did, it's a probing experiment.
It's asking is information present?
Does the model know about charge?
And so, he trains a probe to
ask about charge and then he uses this probe
as a test to different layers of
the model, to different components of the model to say,
where is information about charge in this model?
And he says, oh, it's in the sequence. Part,
it's in the pairwise part, at this layer to
that layer. The problem with this type of probe
is even if the information is
present, the model might not be using
it. Right? If the mation
information is absent, it's really unlikely the
model's using it. Right? If the info
even if the information's present, the model might not
be using it. So so to to see how the
model is actually working, you have to triangulate
it And so he follows this with
a second experiment, and he does it
This one is it's called the
steering experiment. Where he
takes a specific vector vector representation
of charge, which he gets
by taking all the positive residues and all the negative
residues and the representation at a particular
layer, and just taking
the difference the vector difference between
the average positive residue and the average
negative residue and that gives them a
very concrete vector
that just is his hypothesized representation
of charge inside the model.
And then he asks, can you actually
steer the model to behave
as if the charge
as if it's belief of the charge, was
positive or negative by injecting this vector
into the model. Like can we can we
not only read out
the concept of charge from the model, but can we get
the model to think differently by
doing it? So, what he does is
he takes something that is not
not a beta hairpin,
and then he injects positive charge
into one run,
of the, of the model, even if the
actual aminos are not positive. He says,
he says think that these are positive. He says
override the thoughts and then he
injects negative charge into the
adjacent run. And what
this should do is it
should get the model to think it's like a it's like
a little fake chemistry experiment
It should get the model to think that there's a positive
and negative thing adjacent to each other. They
should like magnet together. So it's
really weird. It's like doing it's like doing
chemistry inside the AI
brain. By making it hallucinate that
some of the things are positive when they're not and other things
are negative when they're not. And and the
answer is yes. It absolutely does this.
I'll show you let's see if I have a video.
So this is is an example of him.
Taking something that was charged
one way and then he he gives them both
positive charge on both sides, and then you
can see that he he can
crank open the prediction
so that these things are repelling each other and he can
do the as well. He can pull these things back together
so by making the model believe
the charge is different from what it actually
is, he can get them he can like do chemistry
experiments that are counterfactual
in the real world. So
that's that's another example. Now,
that's that was all sequential stuff. He
also did an interesting set
of experiments looking at the pairwise representation
And in in this case, he found
oh my gosh, slow animations from his
slides He what he found was
that the pairwise representations
actually represent distances like
spatial distances between between
amino acids. And he can,
with a simple linear probe, he
can regress pairwise distances
really accurately. Just just in terms of
angstroms. And
and the interesting thing about that is
that he can take these late
layer pairwise representations
and just physically manipulate the distances
to just to just jam
things together in different locations.
That's that's another way that you can make hairpins.
By taking, the two sides
that aren't a hairpin and then
reducing the, his hypothesized
encoding for the number of angstroms
between them he can he can cause them
to be a hairpin. I'll show you another video of this.
It's kind of interesting. So this
is something that's sort of loosely
folded. And then he says, oh,
actually, want you to hallucinate that these
things should be tighter together, and you can see
that yes indeed
you know, this this representation of hypothesized
risk representation of distance in the
model actually is causal for the way
the model is thinking. So, and
this is this is the stuff that's happening later at layer
30 and so on. So
so you can kind of see, okay, this is this is his main
findings. That early
on, you've got these
chemical properties and later on you have these geometric
properties and the model is
localizing each one of these properties
in low dimensional subspaces
at small numbers of tokens
and you can you can trace
the computation through
so that you can actually cause
the model to behave as
if counterfactual
values are actually held for all these
different concepts, these scientific concepts.
Okay. So
is really the first time somebody's cracked open
a protein folding model to try to see
what signs of the internal computations
are. You can see
that know, even after quite a bit
of effort, we can only understand
very rudimentary things
and it leads you to this question, so
what? You know, what's the
big deal? So you you know, we have
have positive charge and negative charge and we have
you know, angstrom differences you
know, distances between between atoms.
What do we care? That the model is thinking
about these things? None of these things
particularly surprise. Well,
this is really the way I see it is this is really
part of broader
research program, a broader research question.
Which is you know,
if if these models are going to start
understanding things better than humans do,
then how are we going to
with them? They're opaque black box systems.
There's really three things that you'd like to be
able to do that when the systems
are black box is pretty hard to do. So one is
you know, you'd really like to debug, audit,
and improve the models. So
already looking inside the models, it rate the
you know, it raises questions about
the architectures Like, if if
the early layers are all about the
sequence representation and the late layers
are all about the pairwise
representation then we're do are we doing
a lot of unnecessary computation? You
need the sequence representation at layers? Do
you need the pairwise representation at early
layers? Right? Is this we just
you know, sort of throwing in a lot of extra
trained? They're sort of dead.
Are there ways of debugging,
optimizing, and improving the systems, from
the insights that we have. I think that's that's
that's an obvious
type of thing that
the insight that that people will
get from this type of work. But then, there's
other things that are less obvious, which are interesting.
Are there are actually a lot of unsolved problems
in protein folding trying to understand
how folded proteins interact
with each other There are also
proteins that change conformation very
easily under different conditions,
if you change the pH a little bit, they'll change your
conformation and so on. And current,
protein folding models they just
give you a consensus estimation
of what's going on. The interesting thing
about understanding how they're computing is that
it might give you the ability to control
these things in a more precise way. Like
just the way that we can change the charge environment
to a little bit more positive or negative,
at least naturally leads to the question,
can you get the model to do a counterfactual
prediction if you change the pH by a little
bit? If you dial up
the pH can you get the very same
model that you trained on a neutral pH
training set to tell you what its prediction
would have been if
And so so I think that there may
be practical knobs that we can add to these
models based on the things that we understand
in them. That's another research target in the
future. But I'd say that the real research
target the real long term thing
is that these models are
doing predictions. That are
better than all the previous models that we've made before.
They're they're more they're more accurate than you
can get out of quantum mechanics. And so the
question is, are they doing this
based on principles that we should
have in our textbooks? Like
new knowledge about how biological
mechanics works or new rules of
thumb of how protein folding is done.
These these unknown rules of thumb are definitely
encoded in these models scientists
don't know how they're working so well. And so
the question is, can you can
you roll this
knowledge forward of how they're doing their
computations far enough that we can actually
write the next chapter of the textbook.
And that's really the long term vision and the
the challenge that's in front of us. From doing
this. And so, that's
that's that's my perspective. On this type of thing.
I think that a lot of the work that
we're very excited by in the field
has to do with understanding
language models I think that you have
very similar questions that are already being asked
about how do you get superhuman capabilities
out of a coding language
model when you have a language model
that's dealing with vast amounts of text.
Are there types of reasoning that it can
do that actually start
to exceed the ability of humans
to reason and so, how do they work?
But I think that there's the
in a lot of those domains, it's kind of this
open question whether the systems are actually
smarter than all humans yet, or not,
but there are other domains, like the scientific
domains, where it's already unambiguous,
where the existing AI systems
are already outstripping all the previous,
science that has been done. And,
and so we already are confronted with this
question. Of how how to read the science
back out of deep learning systems.
Thank you very much.
So unfortunately, we're out of time, but this
is the break. So if you have questions for David, you
can just with him at
the break. If you need
to the if you need to hang your poster, you
can come to us We have the strips and
we'll resume at eleven.
Later, so if you have
a seat. Can start with the contributor
talks. Thanks.
Please have a seat. Can we
do the poster later, please?
So
I stocked
Okay. So the first contributor
to of the day is by Minak Song.
Who is an undergraduate student, at
Kaist in Korea. Majoring in mathematical
sciences in the group of Charlie Yu,
he was also this is a student at
Washington. And, he works
on bridging Turing a practice
in learning theory.
And, he has a recent focus on optimization
dynamics. So today's going to talk
about zero order optimization at
the adjustability.
Thank you for your
introduction.
Yeah. I would like to thank for organizing this
work. Wonderful workshop.
The first talk of this morning session
was from Jeremy about how
does screen design work? I would like to
expand his talk but and talk
about how does zeros order gradient
descent work. So this was done with
my wonderful collaborators, Liang, Bingzhong,
Yao. Michael, and Sue.
So what is zero sorter optimization?
It is an optimizer method that
optimizes an objective using only function
values which means doesn't use
gradient. Compared to the first order
method. So this is very useful when gradients
are inaccessible, noisy, or too
costly to obtain. So
in modern deep learning, the most famous
method why they use this SPSA,
which is used for a zero order grading estimator.
And one famous example is
called Mezzo, which uses for fine
tuning large language models. We
just forward passes So it doesn't use any
back propagation, so it reduces memory
by 12 times. But achieving the
similar performance. So
and how does zero third degree in the standard
work? So consider minimization
problem of optimizing the objective f.
And the simplest algorithm, there
is sort of gradient set. Updates
using this two point gradient estimator.
Delta hat f. So it's basically
gradient descent, but we replace the
with an update with a gradient estimator.
And to obtain this two point gradient estimator,
you first sample UT
from a standard Gaussian distribution.
So this is your perturbation
vector. And you perturb x
t, the current iterate, through this u
t vector. And obtain two point
function values, which is f x t
plus mu u t and x t minus
mu u t, and compute the final difference.
And you the two point grader
estimator becomes just this scalar times
u t, which is a random vector direction.
And here, mu is a perturbation radius.
And we can note that if
mu goes to zero, then the expectation
of this gradient estimator also converts
to the exact gradient.
And our interest in our this
talk is understand the training dynamics
of this theory of disorder method.
Operating in deep learning.
So let's quickly review how gradient
descent works in learning.
So in gradient descent, with step size ADA,
on a quadratic objective,
We see that the iterate would diverge if the
step size is larger than two over
a maximum value of testing.
But, however, in deep learning,
just showed that full best gradient
descent operates at the edge of stability, which
means that the maximum
value of Tessian is saturating at two over
sub sites.
So to understand the zero sorter grading
let's start with a very simple
experiment, just training convolutional
network on cipher 10.
So here we plot
Hessian top eigenvalue and also Hessian
trees along green the descent. And also
zero order gradient descent. Trajectory.
We used three different jet sizes.
Each by blue orange, and
green colors. So at
the top left figure, you see
that a typical EOS behavior
of Grain is then showing that
the maximum iodine value of HSEAN is
saturating at two over the step
size.
And if you see the figure at the
bottom right, the this is
the evolution of the Hessian trees along the through
sort of gray in the center
And you see somewhat a similar phenomena.
But a bit different So the trace of
HETYAN is now saturating two
array minus some delta. So
it's saturates slightly below this threshold.
So we can speculate that there is something
similar happening for zero to order
grid instead. It's something at job stability, something
related to the trace of s
So the main research questions we want to
answer is first, do zeros order method
also operate at edge of stability in deep learning?
And also, second, if so,
which curvature related quantity covering
this?
So To answer this question, we'll
we'll start with introducing the linearized dynamics
So let x star be x star be a
local minimizer of f and let h
denote the hessian. Metrics at this
x star. Then the
linear dynamics of this optimizer around
this x star is just the dynamics obtained
by applying this optimizer to the
quadratic Taylor approximation around this
x star. And
we will assume that this hessian
is positive semidefinite and
denote the eigenvalues as lambda
one two under the
And based on this linearized dynamic
definition, we will define a linear stability
of the optimizer. So let's
let x t be the iterates
of the linearized dynamics.
And we will say that the optimizer is
linearly stable in the
mean if the expectation of x
t minus x star is bounded
throughout the trajectory for every initialization.
And we'll also introduce the notion of mean
square linear stability which
is defined as if the expectation
of the square norm of x t
minus x star is bounded throughout the trajectory
every initial iteration. And
here, we could easily note that
for deterministic optimizer, there's
no any stochasticity. These two
notions are exactly the same.
And we can naturally introduce the notion
of critical step size, which is
defined as the largest step size that will guarantee
linear stability. So
the critical step size in the mean we will
denote it as a dot
mean star, and we will define the critical
step size in the mean square as ADA
MS star.
So for standard grid and descent, the
linear stability is what we know.
The critical step size of gradient descent
is exactly two of our
maximum eigenvalue you have the Hessian. So if the step size is
smaller than this, it is linearly stable,
If the step size is larger, then the
dynamics would be linearly unstable.
So how about the zero third grader grade in descent?
So one thing to remark is that
since we are considering a quadratic
objective, the two
point estimator is observed to be unbiased
estimator. And therefore,
the mean dynamics of the observed
gradients tend is essentially same as just
standard graded descent. So the
main dynamics are exactly the same, so
our main interest would be
understanding as mean scare dynamics
of theorems that are graded. Descent.
And here is the result for zero third
degree descent. So it
turns out that the critical step
size in the mean square is
a unique solution of ADA that satisfies these
three equations, which is ADA
times lambda max h is smaller than one
and the sum of Ada lambda I over
two times one minus Ada lambda I is exactly
one. So could exactly characterize
this mean square step size.
Critical step size. And moreover,
we could also obtain a lower bound
as two over a trace of hessian plus
two times maximum egg value of hessian.
And upper bound is critical step size
as two over the trace of
of Pesion. So we characterized
as the critical step size of zero third
degree descent, And
if we note that if if you know
the full spectrum of this Hessian,
the exact critical step size can be computed
by solving these equations, But
obtaining the full spectrum is like unlikely
It's infeasible in practice.
So instead we will track upper bound and
lower bound, which is only characterized by
trace. And the hessian maximum
eigenvalue. And these can be
efficiently estimated using just hessian vector plot.
And we also have results
for the momentum and adaptive
method. So if you see this
table, the first top three methods
are first order methods. We know
it's a linear stability condition. And
the bottom three is what we have obtained for
the first order counterparts.
Which is about the critical step size of each
method.
And one thing interesting here
is that if you watch
see the effect of the momentum beta,
here. For so for first order
gradient start with momentum, if
beta increases, then the critical step size also
increases. But for for
but for zero third degree descent, with
momentum, if beta decreases,
then the critical step size will decrease by
one minus beta. And
there's also different effect of beta one
in Adam and zero version.
So we see that the momentum affects the stability
of first order method and second
zero order method in very different ways.
So So in experiments,
we will track the mean square stability during
the training. And we will say
zero sort of gradient standards at mean scale
edge of stability if
two of a data is inside the
boundary of trace of HSE and trace of HSE and
post two times maximum of
HSEAN and also similarly as
zero order gradient semibre momentum and zero
order adder.
And here is what we got for
training CNN on cipher 10.
We again track trace of
HESEN and also trace of HESEN
plus. Two times lambda max of eigenvalue.
And you see you see this upward bound and
lower bound and the dash line, which
is two arrear.
And this dash line is exactly be
is exactly between these two values, which
means that zero zero zero zero zero zero zero
zero is indeed at the minisker edge
of several
We also did got similar observation,
not only for zero sorter grain descent, but
also for the of the of the of this time
with momentum when varying this
And also for zero order Adam.
At right speaker. We
also changed architectures to
ResNet vision
transformer, and
all these setup, we observed that they all
So And finally,
we could also,
clearly observe these catapults dynamics,
we increase the step size at the middle of the
training. So we increased step
size from ADA one to ADA two and ADA
two to ADA three. Three. And you
see that the
trace of HSM decreases as
you increase the zap size, and there's a
loss spike is a catapod dynamic
which is a similar observation we could observe
for gradient descent when you increase the step size.
So So quick summary.
We obtained the exact
step size calculation for
understanding the mean scale linear stability
for a family of zero order optimizers.
And that includes gradient descent.
The original version of gradient descent, and its momentum
and preconditioned variance. Which
is series order atom. And
empirically, we observed that the full
batch of orders are operating
at the mean scale edge of stable.
So the takeaway is
that when we use a large step sizes,
for zeroth order training, this is implicitly
biasing your solution
with small preconditioned Hessian traits.
Or just small which
is different as compared to first order
training, which is leading you to
small hessian maximum Eigen value.
So here, his entries is
much important. For understanding through his
order training. And
some future works, we could
think about central flow for this zero to the
gradient stand. And also
another future work would be,
understanding edge up stability for a series order stochastic
gradient descent. Where we use mini
batches.
Yeah. That's all. And we
also have these archived version of our
full papers. If you're interested, you can check
out. Thank you.
Thank you, Minak. Are
there questions?
Please, can walk to the mic or
I can come with
you.
If no, let's thank Minak again.
Thank you.
So the next contributor
talk of the day is by
She's a PhD student in the theory
of computation group at Columbia
University. And she's advised by
Daniel Tsue and Alex Andoni.
Before that, she majored in mathematics
and computer computer science at,
UC San Diego. And,
her research is in, machine learning
theory and
algorithm statistics. And, specifically
finding methods to make training
more efficient. And, today,
she will talk about less data
and faster training.
Please.
Thanks for the introduction. I'm Jing
Wen Liu from Columbia University.
Today, I'll be presenting our
work on less data faster training.
And specifically, how repeating a
smaller dataset can actually speed up
optimization. This is joint work with Ezra
Edelman and Sirbi Goh from University of
Pennsylvania. And Bing Bin Liu
from Computer Institute and Harvard University.
So from the classical point
of view for deep learning, more data is
always better. And
the scaling law of training LOMs also indicates worse
test loss under the data constraint setting.
But can less data be favorable
in any cases? Prior
work has found that under a fixed compute
budget, moderate number of repetitions
on smaller dataset can
actually do much better than training on
large data set for some mass reasoning
tasks like common
divisor and modular multiplication.
We further investigate this
phenomenon across several different
setups.
We We first compare re
repeating on smaller dataset with online
training in transformers, and
using Adam optimizer on four
different tasks. Sparse parity,
single image model, in context learning
linear regression, and modular addition.
And we found out that repeating on smaller
datasets with which corresponding
to the orange curves, converges much
faster than online training which corresponding
to the blue curves.
So also tried this on
MLPs using mini batch gradient descent.
And, again, repeating
on smaller dataset learns much
faster than using fresh data at each step.
And this also holds for full
batch gradient descent. Which means
each step, we perform gradient descent on the
entire dataset In this setting,
we compare full batch GED on smaller
dataset versus large dataset.
So we call this phenomenon the small
versus large gap.
And I've shown that the small versus
large gap exist across
different setups, for example, different
tasks, different architecture, and different optimizers.
Which indicates that repeating smaller
data set can actually be a
favorable inductive bias for optimization.
And we aim to understand why this
happens. I'll first
explain why the existing theory cannot
explain this, and then present
our hypothesis formalized by theory
and supporting empirical evidence.
For this talk, we just gonna focus on
the parity task. Formally,
a decay parity takes input drawn uniformly
from a d dimensional
hypercube. There's, hidden
support set hidden support
s of size k. And
the label is the parity on the
coordinates in the support s.
So Okay.
There are some prior work that showed that repetition
can make SGD algorithm
go beyond CXQ algorithm.
And have the power of SQL algorithm,
which is a much more powerful class
But for a parity, there's no distinction
between the C SQ and the SQL lower bond.
And another explanation could be
repeating on smaller dataset can reduce the
gradient variance. But this doesn't
apply to the full batch GED case.
Where there's no gradient variance involved.
And some other work also
also show that
if the input distribution is biased,
there are some low lower order
signal that can be exploited. But the signal
decays exponentially in k, which can
be very weak k is large.
But we still observe the small versus large
gap in the dense parity setting.
So our hypothesis is that the sampling
bias from the smaller dataset
can help adjust the relative norm across
layers a desirable way.
To be more clear, the sampling bias
of a dataset of size n is roughly on
the order of one over square root of n.
And repeating on a small dataset
keeps reinforcing this bias which
leads to the rapid growth of some layers.
Let me illustrate the intuition on
the two layer MLP setting.
The sampling bias can grow the norm of the
second layer which is the parameter
a, very fast, and
which in turn speed up the feature learning in the
first layer for w.
Because the gradient of w depends on the gradient,
depends on the normal a.
And we also empirically observed this
Here, we can see that in the smaller
data the smaller data set grows the
ratio norm ratio between a and
w. Much faster than larger
dataset. At the initial phase of
training.
We further formalized this, intuition,
you know, two layer quadratic
activation model with correlation loss.
We analyze a two phase training strategy
where we first train on random subset
of the population with size n,
and then switch to training on the full
population. And the
simulation also aligns with our
intuition that the first phase
smaller data set grows the a faster, and
this induced faster feature learning in the second
phase. And we can prove
that in this setting, the number of
steps needed for convergence is smaller when
the data set size n is smaller.
Okay. So far, I've I've been showing
you the theoretical intuition for the
hypothesis. Next, I
will present some empirical evidence
our hypothesis. Since the
role of sampling bias
is to grow the second layer,
The any approach that grows the norm of the
second layer fast should also give
similar speed up. And the signal
doesn't have to be relevant to the target function.
Therefore, we test our hypothesis
by first repeating on a smaller
dataset with random labels.
And then switching to the large dataset.
Here in the, figure, the green
curve is training with a random
label. And we can see that it is
comparable to the orange
curve is repeating on a smart data
set with true true label.
And on the right, the
growth rate of the norm ratio between first layer and
second layer only depends on the size of the
smaller dataset.
We can also directly initialize the
second layer norm. To to be
larger than first layer. And
in this figure, the x axis
is the unit scale for the first layer, and the y axis
is the scale unit scale for second
layer. And the lighter color means the better
accuracy. The red star
denotes the sender initialization scale.
And, indeed, we see that
large set training is much faster when
the scale of the second layer is larger and the first
layer scale is smaller.
So in this case, we can see that
at the best layer wise, initialization
scale the small versus large gap can be closed.
But repeating on smaller data set
is much more robust on different
initial initialization scale.
We can also, instead of
growing the norm of the second layer,
we can also just directly use layer
wise learning rate. This can also
close a small versus large gap.
Here, the dash lines are using the optimal
layer wise learning rate. Which is which
uses a much larger learning rate for the
second layer than the first layer.
So We further confirm our intuition
on the transformer model
where we focus on only the QK
matrices. Because it directly
affects the attention part of the transformer,
And we found that increasing the learning rate
for the QK or increasing
the initialization scale for QK
And adding QK normalization can also
reduce the small versus large gap.
So Finally, I want to discuss,
some setting which can make the
small versus large gap larger.
First, we observe that the gap
grows significantly larger as the model
gets deeper.
Or the model width gets smaller.
And or the or the task is
being more complex.
Okay. To summarize, we found that
repeating on smaller dataset can be a favorable
inductive bias in optimization.
It it it can give speed up comparable
to exhaustively tuning tuning
learning layer wise learning rate. Or layer wise initialization
scale. The latter
can be very computationally
expensive. To tune when the model gets deeper
and deeper.
And we'd identified that the speed up
is mainly due to the larger
sampling bias from the slower data set.
Which gives favorable relative norm growth
between layers.
I Okay. You might wonder, when does
the small versus large gap exist?
We believe that the loss landscape
needs to be nonconverged and have many
saddle points.
And we confirm that it doesn't exist in
the linear regression setting.
Connecting to practice we don't
think the small versus large gap exists
in when the training data is already
very redundant.
And this is the case in LMPT
training on on large web dataset.
However, believe that
this exists when the
when we're training on more structured data.
Such as formal reasoning tasks,
And this has been confirmed by a
concurrent work, which also demonstrates a small
small versus large gap in RNN post training
for mass encoding datasets.
Okay. I will conclude my talk from here.
Thanks for listening, and happy to take any
questions.
Thanks to the speaker. Are there
questions?
Thank you for great talk. So,
based on your theory, is it
possible to suggest how many samples
we should use or mean,
any idea? So
before starting training, it's it possible?
Oh, yeah. I think the the it's
pretty robust across the,
hyperparameters. So just make
sure the the smaller
dataset is small enough
so that, training,
the training loss can quite quickly overfit
to the small dataset. And then later
use a large data set to ensure generalization
and this will generally give speed up.
Sorry. But the too small, it it overfits.
Right? So So that it it can
quickly overfits to
the training data. And that the best
number of samples can
can we see beforehand?
Sorry. What what what do you mean by that? We don't like overfitting.
Right? Oh, oh,
slightly overfitting is okay. And
Slightly. Yes. Yeah. Slightly. But but, I mean, just
one sample is Oh, yeah. Like, yeah.
It Yeah. It it has to learn
some meaningful, stuff from the
task. Yes. And my question is about
maybe lower bound of
number of samples you need
we don't have a rigorous lower bound, but,
I think, first, like, your model needs
to significantly from the
insertion. And
that's that's the general strategy.
Okay. Thank you. Yeah.
Other questions?
If not, let's thank Jing Wen.
Thank you.
Next speaker, is, Bruno
Lorero. He's a
CENRS researcher at the Ecole Normale
in Paris in the center for data
science. He's a
prominent figure in statistical physics
using, methods that come from, disorder
systems theory. To crack problems
in, machine learning. Theory.
And today, he's going to talk about optimal
scaling loads in learning year after multi
index models. And, Bruno.
Florin. Thank you for the nice
introduction, Antonio. So, yeah. Today
I'm gonna be presenting you this work with my
PhD student Leonardo De Felipe, and my
great collaborators Anton Meyer. And
Fillon Jacalab. So before
starting to the paper, I would like to
share with you, like, this which
is an extract of a paper written by Liu
Brimon think is very much in the spirit of
this workshop where he's advocating
that our fields would be better off with
fewer terms, less emphasis on FADG stuff,
and much more scientific inquiry in engineering
but the latter requires real thinking.
So actually the reason why I put
this slide is because, you know, as a physicist thinking
about theory of machine learning,
essentially, I'm both like
a believer and a preacher of this
philosophy, and, of the workshop
philosophy. But this paper that I'm gonna
be presenting to you today, probably
one of the most kind of mathematical and TCS
like paper that I that I have.
So, yeah, that's an apology, and I tried to make
it as scientific as possible.
For this workshop. So let's get
going. So what is the key
scientific idea in this paper?
Is this notion that feature learning can be
understood as a spectral
transition in the weights of neural network.
So here, I'm showing you some empirical evidence
from different, papers by some colleagues,
who have been looking at that empirically.
Have been showing that throughout the training, as you train your
neural network, the spectrum of your weights
going from being like the spectrum of a random
matrix that's in because you start
at initialization, with random weights,
and then as you train, you get, like,
spikes that get out of the bulk, and these
are associated with feature learning.
Now, these are empirical observations and
some of my work over the past few years have been
trying to understand this like, in simple
models much much in, like, in the same philosophy as,
Jeremy was advocating the first talk.
So, we have studied a lot, like,
feature learning in what is called like multi index
models, which are kind of models
that translate this inductive
bias that data leaves in a
low dimensional sub and so you
know, learning features mean to learn these directions,
which are hidden. And
so we had a lot of papers about that, where you
can make very concrete this idea that,
you know, at initialization, or when you
have very little data, you're
truly in your network weights are essentially
random, so you cannot capture anything
about the information on the data, and as you do
grading descent or as you add more data,
you start correlating with these hidden directions
in this multinox model. So, you get, like, this
kind of spectra transition with a spike
out of the bulk, and this spike is correlating with
this directions w
one, w, r. And so, as you
keep increasing or you keep training more, like, you
get more and more spikes, and then you can
see like as the networks get better and
better in generalization, essentially what you're having is
like more and more spikes. So, this
has been, worked in the different papers,
that I'm I'm citing here.
So, the goal of this paper, specifically,
is trying to make sense of,
new scaling laws using this framework.
So, for those of you who don't know
nearest scaling laws, this has been an empirical observation
that had major impact
in practice over the past few years. And
essentially challenges this traditional point of view
that more is better. Right? Like,
I keep increasing my network, gonna get
better and better. So, that turns
out not to be true, unless you actually scale different
quantities together. So, both
the number of parameters, the quantity of data,
and the amount of compute that you spend.
And actually, empirically, you can describe
this relationship as
a power law into these three parameters.
So, this is an empirical observation
in large language models. And from
the theoretical perspective, we do
have some understanding of this phenomena of scaling
laws, but mostly on linear methods
or lazy training.
And I guess, have some people in the audience
that have worked on that as well. I have worked on that.
And actually, this kind of saturation phenomena
that you get if you just scale one of these parameters
without keeping, like, keeping the other
fixed, can actually be understood in these
kernel methods, and so here, just showing two plots
from my own work. Or have studied that.
But, as I said, many
colleagues have worked on that, and guess that
we pretty much understand this
saturation phenomena in linear models.
So, lately, I have been thinking a lot on how
can we make sense of,
putting together feature learning
and scaling? And in particular, how
scaling improves as you train
and as you learn features. Because in all these
cases, essentially, the
weights of the neural network are random or fixed.
So you don't have, like, this adaptivity,
which is so important when you actually
deal with real neural networks.
So, the starting point, on this journey
has been this paper that actually
we presented as an oral here, at a clear
last Friday. In
which we studied this problem in the context
of quadratic neural networks. And,
again, I'm gonna resonate on what Jeremy
said, like, you know, we should start
by whatever is simpler, and more
complicated than a linear model is
a quadratic model.
So, this defines a class of
tasks, which you can see as like a composition
of several quadratic polynomials,
and this composition is hierarchical. Meaning that,
you know, lower order terms
in this composition are less
are more important, and then as you go up
in the sum, the different directions that,
that are in this multi index model, they are less and
less important. And you can think learning
in this problem as, hierarchically, learning
these different tasks.
And the power law comes from the fact that as you
aggregate the tasks,
you know, you have this, like, decaying
importance. So, in this paper that we presented
on Friday, essentially, we
have a theory to describe learning,
of this model with a quadratic
network. So, this is a quadratic task
can be learned with a quadratic network, and essentially,
we have a whole phenomenology of how different
scalings on this problem
appear in terms of
different spectral transitions on the weights.
And a crossover between different scalings,
just like as is observed
in the neuro, scaling laws in LLMs,
can be described in this simple model, in
terms of crossovers between different rates, which are associated
to different spectral regimes into the neural
network. So, the question we
posed into this paper that I'm
discussing here today is, yeah.
Quadratic is nice, but, you know, we
would like to say something about two linear networks
in general. So can we go beyond quadratics?
And so the natural candidate for that would
be instead of having, like, a sum of quadratic
tasks, now we have a hierarchical sum
of of different tasks
with like, you know, activations, which
is are more general than quadratics.
And the main idea is to use this
is a kind of spectral transition
picture to see if we can say something about
that. Now, this is a
slightly harder problem than for quadratic neural
networks, but
some things can be said. So,
the first result in this paper
is essentially saying that the rates
of the quadratic network learning
this hierarchical composition of quadratic tasks,
is universal, in the sense that
for any activation that has,
what we call, like, an information exponent too,
so you can think about, like, just
even activations.
The rates that the neural network achieve
are the optimal rates. So
here, is described by these two rates here
in these two different regimes. So the
way we prove this in this paper
is, you know, in a very good, TCS fashion.
It's like to do a upper and lower bound
of the of the of the risk, So
let me give you some intuition.
So the upper bound is
basically building on a line
of work on spectral methods, so we we propose
a spectral method, analyze that
the you know, the top eigenvectors of this spectral
method correlate with the directions
at the rate that is given
here. So, at least, we have this upper
bound saying that, you know, if you have this spectrum
method, that the
the optimal rate can only be smaller
than that. So, these build
on lines of work, that I'm putting here
below, also by people in the audience.
So, the lower
bound instead we consider,
an oracle that says, you know, imagine that you have
learned all directions except one.
And now the complexity of
learning in this direction goes
back to a single index model, and it turns
out that we understand very well,
how like, the optimal error goes
for learning single index models in terms
what is what is called, like, the free energy potential,
And, this gives us, a lower
bound. So this is like, the
first result saying that, you know,
we have more general activation, we can achieve
the optimal rates
efficiently with this you
know, two two,
algorithms. Now, the second
main result in the paper it's,
what happens when you get, like, actually truly in
your network? Because a truly a neural network, you
know, is not implementing this spectral
method, or this oracle.
So, what we can show here, is not
as strong as what we can show for the quadratic
network, but we do
we can show that if you consider a is still
is a lies version of gradient descent, where
first, you do a spectral
initialization on the first layer weights,
and then you train the second layer weights by doing
ridge regression. You can
prove that the rates that I showed
you before, so the optimal rates,
actually can be achieved by the
two layer neural network. And
so, this this uses, again, like builds
up on, some recent progress, both
on spectral methods, and on considering
ridge regression with correlated
features. So
this is just showing you, like, a little plot that,
that show you, like,
optimal rates and the crossover. Between
the two optimal rates. When you're learning
different target functions, which have
this information exponent true,
with this with this, this stabilized version
of gradient descent, where you separate, like,
you know, first subspace recovery,
and then feeding the second
layer. Like the nonparametric
part. Okay. So this
is essentially what we do in the paper,
let me conclude. So, what do we did I
show you today? I showed you that, feature
learning can be understood as spectral transitions
on the weights of the neural networks.
I showed you that, the hierarchical
multinix models are natural models for
studying scaling laws in this feature
learning regime, And, finally, I showed you that, you
know, two layer neural networks
trained in this stabilized version of, gradient
descent can achieve these optimal rates
efficiently. So, if you want to know more about
the technical details, which I didn't cover
here, I have a poster
here. So, you know, this I think
is the last talk of the contributor talk.
So, you know, if you want, can go
come and check chat with me. So that's
the paper. Again, thank you for my collaborators,
and if you have questions, I'm happy to take it.
Thank you, Bruno, for the talk.
Other questions?
Do you expect, similar
phenomena if instead
of a sum or single index model, I have a
multi index model, but somehow
each additional coordinate influences less
and less the output. Like, is there something special about
the separability here or No. That's
that's a good question. Actually, there is nothing special. Actually,
in the paper, we we we can
deal with the case that you are just a bit tricky
to define what means like, less and less important,
an environment way, but, but
we we can we can handle this case as well.
So the separability is not important.
The the hierarchical structure that different
directions require, let's say,
different directions are more important than the others,
and they the gap between
them of know, follows this kind of powerless
structure. Is what is important.
Other questions?
Okay. Saks, bring on over a talk.
I have a question about your last
part, So if we use a
special initialization, so what is
the time in
of this phase? So it will be the log
d. Time or it will
something like this? Yeah. Indeed. If
you if you if you're doing, like,
you know, power iteration, that would be a log
d. Yeah. Yeah. So, okay. This is
my following question. So I
find that not just in sync on text model
or marketing app model, Also,
in other settings, I
find a very in switch
interesting theoretical performance is.
When we have the two stages two
free transitions, normally, in the
first phase, normally, we'll take
the log d or log d some step.
And then in the second phase, you
it will normally enter in a lazy
or the linear regimes. We'll take the form
of exponential. And learning
rate or something like convergence rates. So I'm
wondering, do you have some thoughts about this? So
I I I don't think you can get rid of the log d.
So at least for this class where you have, like,
information exponent two functions, you
always have like this saddle initialization. So
I think you cannot get rid of these, like,
log d factor in time.
Yeah. Yeah. So in real life, the
hierarchical structure has a linear part.
Probably, like, you get rid of the linear
part first, and then you get into
this trouble. Having to to deal with
the log d of the quadratic part, but I don't think
you can get rid of that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Thanks.
Other questions?
If not, let's thank Bruno.
Thank you.
And now we have the poster session.
To have more discussions. If
you wanna continue
Hello. Hello. We're gonna resume,
with our next talk So
if you would please mosey over
to your seats, turn
your eyes away from the
extremely well composed and attention grabbing
posters.
And we'll have a talk in
a few minutes.
Thank you.
Alright. Let's start.
So our next speaker is professor
Rich Bronick. He's a professor
of, electrical engineering
computer science and statistics at
Rice University He has
made major contributions
to and classical signal
processing, like multi scale
image models, compressive
sensing, and many more. And more
recently, he has been an advocate at free
and open source education.
And today, he's going to tell us about
what happens when generative models
consume their own output. Very fun.
And creative research. Thanks.
How's that going? Working? Okay.
It's great. Hello everybody.
Great to be here.
And to talk a little bit about
the science of
self consumption in AI.
And I'd like to dedicate this talk to
Tan. Who this
morning was given the award
coming from the furthest away
to ICLR. So let's give Tann a
round of applause.
Okay. This is joint work with some,
some of my students and,
collaborators. So thanks. In,
and MTI's and Atlas.
So I have a quick
question. Does anybody here have
enough data?
Nobody has enough data. You have enough nobody
has enough data. I mean we're running out of data.
We're either running out of data or
we have run out of data.
And this is means that we're gonna be in
a situation where performance
is gonna be harder and harder to improve.
In let's talk in just as
talk about, in generative modeling.
Okay? Now, some of you will say, wait a
minute, we're not running out of of data. The world
is full of data. We're
generating huge amounts of data
every day, using
a whole variety of different generative
models. And so a very simple
thing to realize, wait a minute, Why
don't we train our next generation
generative AI models Why don't we train them on synthetic
data? Right? Like, why
not? Everybody's doing it. Right?
Everybody's doing it, so why why shouldn't we?
Right? Now some of you in the room will
be a bit kind of reticent to bit
bit kind of conservative, and you'll say, okay,
No. I wanna be super
clean. And I'm only going to train
on verified real data
sets that have been created by
careful curators. Right? Data sets like
Leon b, or Leon five b.
Which happens to be polluted with a
huge amount of synthetically generated
images. Right? And so it's
just inevitable, unfortunately, that
we're just moving into a world
where we're gonna be learning new
models, by
you know, using the real data that's out there, but also
by consuming data that's
produced by similar or
previous generation
synthetic Gen AI
model? And so this talk, I just want to address
two sides of this the science
of of this issue, the
first is you know, what can go wrong
when this when we do this? And then the second
is is there anything that we can actually
do about it? Okay? So part one,
let's talk about very simply
this this idea that you could think
you could call self training. So what
is self training? Self training is
the purest idea of using
Gen AI to train
or improve Gen AI. So you start
on the left, with a
hopefully very nicely curated
real right, real data set, You
learn a model, and then,
you fine tune that model or
improve and using out
the outputs in this purest
of situations from that very same
model. Right? This is called self
training. You can see it's creating a
some kind of self consuming feedback loop.
You can do this over many generations,
and you would hope that as you continue
to train with more and more of this synthetic
data, your performance will
increase. And unfortunately, what happens
is it it doesn't increase.
Okay? It actually creates models
that go that go mad.
Right? That go that go kind of crazy
what happens is performance actually deteriorates.
Rather than improves. And by deteriorates,
I mean both in terms of let's say metrics
like FID goes up instead
it goes down. And also
an increasing number of
a these striations
on on the imagery that's generated.
K? So this is one example of using
a model to trying to fine
tune it on itself and
and and going into some kind of madness.
If if you
push it even further and say, well, now I'm
going to use models that are
biased towards producing
high quality output. There's
two ways to do this. First,
very many general AI models out
there ship with the knobs
tuned towards generating more, like,
high quality images, which are closer
to the modes right, of the
distribution. Also,
people will generate imagery,
Right? Imagery using these models.
And they're not gonna they don't put the bad examples
up on the web. Right? They repost
the good examples, and they cherry pick.
And this is another kind of bias. And
bias models actually run into a
special kind of madness, that you've probably heard
of, and it's called collapse. Here's an
example taking
StyleGAN two model, the is a
classic generative model,
and again, fine tuning it based on itself
generation one, generation
two, three, four,
and five. And you see that basically the distribution
of this model, the kind of images it can create,
are basically collapsing to this one
to this one, person.
Right? So there's been some initial
science analyzing these situations.
Some work, out of my group some
work from the Shumilov brothers.
Julia's group. Where's Julia? She's here
somewhere. Starting to study
some of the, implications
of of this
self training. And and we do
know some things. Right? We don't know everything,
but we know some things. First, we
know that this this this
idea of training on
synthetic data basically leads to a distribute
leads to the distribution, the synthetic distribution
taking a random walk.
Right? So it just walks around space,
what our distribution space. And what that
means is that basically any performance
metric that you might pick is gonna deteriorate
because the the true
distribute the the true distribution and the
synthesized distributions are gonna become
further and farther apart as you do this random
walk. Moreover, if you have biased
sampling, like we talked about, the variance
of that distribute, synthesized distribution
is actually going to collapse. Down
to zero. Right?
Thinking in terms of metrics, machine
learning metrics, like precision and recall.
Either precision or recall or
both are gonna decrease And
AMP artifacts like we saw earlier are going
to going to increase.
K? There's a lot of since we're talking about science,
there are a lot of analogies with these
kind of positive feedback
loops. One is in biology. The is
basically inbreeding. Right? We're creating
a kind of Habsburg AI.
Okay? And another very
apt analogy is is to
mad cow disease. Right? Which basically
where it's kind of extremely apt
because it was basically from animals
that were fed brains
of dead animals. Right?
And we're what we're doing is feeding AI
brains right, on
previous generation AI brains.
Okay. Another, analogy is from
mathematics and control theory. This is
basically, you can think of using ideas like
positive feedback loops from control,
Martingale theory, contraction
mapping. A lot of these ideas
have have been useful in trying to analyze
what what happens, when we train models.
On their own But there's still,
like, a ton of open
questions in this space, and let's just go
through them really quick. The first is,
everything that I've talked about up to now, at least the examples
that I showed, are pretty idealized.
Right? You're taking a some
diffusion model, and you're training it on
the output of that very same diffusion model.
Right? This allows you
to prove really nice theorems, but
course, this is not what's actually gonna happen
in practice. So what we need to do is think
about more realistic training
scenarios. What happens when you train a
diffusion model on the output from
say, a StyleGAN? Right?
Or some brand new model with the output
of some state of the art, let's say,
autoregressive type model.
So
the fact that the
big hyperscaler companies are
are trying to do things like data
filtering, data verification. Folks
talk about watermarking in imagery,
even though it's very easy to easy
to turn off, and most users actually
do turn it off. But
this this this key idea, I think, of of trying
to make things more realistic The second is
if you just read the popular press, there's
a tremendous amount of buzz out there about
the fact that that
AI slop is starting to pollute
that not only the the
Internet, but also the the training
pools future AI models And I
think a really interesting problem is actually
looking at going out, looking at
data today versus data, say,
five years ago, eight years ago, and
actually seeing if we can detect that some of
these positive feedback loops are starting
to to activate. I think that'd be
a really interesting really interesting
problem.
Very related, is the idea that
as these models as
like AI type models might collapse,
or might drift away from reality,
Who are the consumers of these models? Well,
humans consume the outputs of these models.
How is that going to affect our brains? Right?
That There's this very
interesting psychological question
about about how this AI collapse could
actually cause some amount of,
like, human brain.
Collapse. And then finally, the thing that
I'd like to talk about for the rest of the talk
is around basically,
is this a dead end? Like, are we doomed?
Right? Or is generative AI doomed because of
this? Or actually, is it
possible for us to build
either, generative AI methods that are resilient
to synthetic data, Right? Or,
like, that's at the very least And at the
very best, we somehow use
we somehow do that, turn this this
what seems like a problem into an opportunity?
K? So that's what I'd like to talk about for the next
next few minutes.
That is addressing this open question,
right, which is can we
actually use the output of
synthetic AI generators
to actually truly improve the performance
of synthetic AI generators. And
it turns out that you can.
Right? But the critical thing is that you
need to treat the real data the
You can't just lump them together
If you lump them together, we are doomed.
But if you treat them, consider them separately,
it's actually possible to improve
models, and that's what I'd like to talk about.
The key the key realization
is that this progression, going
back to the very first
is of
collapse or going mad, this
performance degradation, right, from left to right,
right, as we go from
a model trained on real data to a model
that's been trained successively on
synthetic data, it turns out that there are
signals embedded embedded
in this progression that are extremely
informative, Right?
They're informative about the the
degradations and biases in the generative
model. It's and and
this signal can actually be used to
ameliorate those biases
and those degradations. And I'd like to talk
about just one example of how
you how you can do that. Okay?
So here's a here's an example
of of of
kind of the the the basic setup here.
Let's say that we wanna learn
some, you know, generative model,
and we've trained it on, let's say ImageNet,
Okay? So we've trained our in our generative model
on ImageNet. And the
ideal set of parameters right, if
we had infinite data, is
like over, let's say over there,
in that corner of the room. So that's
theta star is way in the
corner of the room. That's the best possible
parameter. We've trained our
model on ImageNet, So we don't
have those parameters. We have the parameters that
are right here in the middle of my chest.
Okay? These are the parameters They're
pretty good. Right? But we'd like to be better. So
how can we improve our model? There's two
ways that you can think of it. Doing it.
The first is you could go
out and actually acquire more
real data. Right? You could
do that. You go you've trained on ImageNet, you
go you know, poll the
world and and get a whole bunch more
like, real real another million
ideal, real images.
And then what it it turns out is that if
you now fine tune on
those real images, and compute
the gradient, from this point
that would improve the set of parameters, it should
be clear if you have more real data,
the gradient is going to point towards the corner
of the room. Everybody see that? Nodd
of the head. Okay. But of course,
we we we can't go get more data. We're stuck.
Right? We just have we're stuck with the model
that we have. So the the alternative is
to say, well, let's generate a whole bunch
of images from my model,
and then let's fine tune on those images.
Okay? Well, of course, we're not gonna the gradient
with to the
towards a better model. It's going to take us
towards madness. It's going to take us out this
way. Okay? And
so this is where you would you might think, okay,
I'm doomed. There's nothing I can do
because if I fine tune on this
on on the synthetic data, I'm just gonna
move away from my ideal parameter.
K? But if we it it just turns out, and
it it it sort of
was extreme surprise to us,
It turns out that
this direction is this bad direction
is basically the negative
of this good direction.
Okay. It seems crazy, but it's true.
Okay. So if you define what we call
the alignment, which is just the
cosine similarity between this
gradient direction, the bad one,
and the good one, Okay.
What we what we can actually show if you go to the very
bottom of the slide, is actually the inner product
between these is negative. Which
means if you right, which means that
if you flip the bad direction,
it's actually going to point more or less
towards that corner of the room. Okay?
And this is something that we've established
you know, theoretic, like rigorously.
For a a a really important case
of of generative models
that are called mode seeking sampler.
K? And it turns out that, like, most
of the certainly image generators
out there, that are
used both in the literature and that are
used are what are called mode seeking
samplers. And the key idea of a mode seeking sampler
is it introduces a bias
when it samples from its learned distribution.
Okay? So the the the generative model
has learned this blue this nice blue
distribution. But when it actually generates
images from that blue distribution, It's actually
set up to generate them
closer to the modes Right?
And, than out in the tails. And
so what tends to happen is with these mode seeking
samples, you tend to get
mode amplification and tail
attenuation. And we can actually take
that into account to show
these directions are actually the
negative. Of each other. Okay? Hopefully,
this makes sense. We call this
idea neon,
and we call this idea of
taking this bad direction and flipping
it around. We call it negative
extrapolation. Because we're not extrapolating
away extrapolating in this negative
direction. So here's the basic idea
of how this works. It is just extraordinarily
simple. So let's go back to
our setup. We have our model.
We've trained it on real data.
Okay? We actually don't even need to know the
real data that it was trained on. K?
We have our parameters. Of
of the of the model, theta r.
And then what we do is we generate a few
just a few more synthetic images
directly from that generative model.
Okay? And then we take a we take
compute the gradient. Right?
Well, and then we just basically optimize
fine tune with those images. You don't need gradient.
We just fine tune with those
images to create a new model
Right? Same architecture, new parameters,
with parameters theta s.
Okay? And then what we do is rather
than use the model with parameters
theta r, the original model,
or the parameters with theta s,
the new parameters, we combine them.
Basically merge them such that
we're basically, essentially doing
Theta r minus theta s.
With a sum like step. Step size
w. K? So it's an extraordinarily
simple algorithm and it's basically
just a a parameter. Merging.
Super simple, but it works like super well.
K. So here's an example of taking the x a
r l model which is a
high performing high performing
image generative model. Okay?
Some, four examples of images from
synthesized from that model in the top.
I'd actually never seen a car like that in the upper
left until I got here to Rio. And
realized that there actually is a car that looks
like that. So what we did is
we took that model, and then what
we did was we just compute it was trained on ImageNet,
lots of images. We generated
just a thousand more images.
Tiny number of images. Fine
tuned on just those thousand images,
k. It turns out it was like about 3.3%
additional compute And then we
combined, right, Theta r and Theta s
in this neon way, and kind of
magically, the FID drops
about 25%. Right?
So just crazy how well you can
improve a model by
exploiting the fact that you know there's a degradation
happening Right? And you
can account for it by
by just a few few samples.
Okay? So so the thing I wanna you
know, get across here is that this idea is
like super practical. It's just
a simple parameter merge
You don't need anything extra. There's no
extra model. There's no inference.
Change. There's barely any additional
computation. You don't need
access to the original data. It could be
know, a pre trained model. It
works for any mode
seeking sampler, which is, like I said,
almost every almost every
image generator and tons of
text generators, as well.
And it's extremely efficient
and based on actual theory.
Right? So Euro loves it.
He said that it, it lights it
lights his fire. Okay.
So just couple quick example, you know,
to some some, like,
showing you that, you know, the trade offs
and and, you know, how performance improves
From left to right, we are we have the F
FID We have the,
actually here we're just looking at FID. As
we as we basically
vary the number of synthetic images
right, that we're using to fine tune on
when we're varying this
w parameter, which controls how much we merge
in this bad direction.
But the the point is you can see that all of these
curves have basic the same shape,
and this is across diffusion, and
flow matching models. Autoregressive
models, inductive moment matching
models, all basically the same. That there's
a w right, that you can find with
a simple grid search, that's,
you know, substantially
improves on the FID
using just a very small number
of additional synthetic images.
Okay? There's
if, you know, you can't get something for nothing,
there's a no free lunch result.
And that is you can't improve both precision
and recall using this method.
Turns out that
what this neon in particular
does is it tends to squash down the
mode pull up
the tails a little bit of the distribution.
So that causes recall to rise,
precision to fall, but recall
basically rises more than precision falls, and
so the net effect is that the FID
actually improves. So there could
be situations where you're,
know, you you can't sacrifice any recall,
but if you're I mean, precision, but
if you're you're willing to this this
method is gonna improve FID
substantially. And I just will mention,
there's not really any time to talk
about it today, but if you're a fan of class
free guidance like CFG,
you can combine it and neon
to basically
have it kinda have it both ways. So the
precision falls very, very slightly.
But recall rises substantially. But
that's something I can talk about with
folks after. K. We have
been exploring some variants
of this idea, in fact,
neon was based on an earlier method that
we have called SIMS,
and SIEMs is basically the same idea.
This idea of degradation direction,
and then merging right,
the degraded and the pre
trained models together. But it does it
not in parameter space, but in score functions
space. So it it's merging, like,
in the in the distributions.
It turns out, this method also works
really quite well. It
it it designed for working
just with diffusion models, so it's not as
general as as Neon. It's also
a little bit more expensive. Neon is basically
free. But
with with, Sims,
you actually have to have to
actually change the inference algorithm, so it's about
two times two times more expensive.
But the really interesting thing, like scientifically,
about SIMs, is it turns
out that it works
continues to work really well even
if the original data
the the supposed real data,
that you used to train your model on originally,
was polluted with synthetic
synthetic data. Okay? And
this is really quite a strong
effect. We see that, you know, you can have up to like
10 or 15% of
pollution, you have this resiliency,
which I I think is very attractive.
But this is something we totally don't understand.
We have no idea why this is the case,
but it's just a a very nice, I think,
open question. For somebody out there,
to look into. Okay. So just
to wrap up, I
think hopefully it's clear to people
that you know, to some extent, some kind
of madness or
or collapse or some
variant thereof, I think is inevitable
as we move forward
in this, you know, gen AI
increasingly gen AI world,
but but rather than just viewing it
as a kind of it would as
a dooms day kind of
idea. I believe that if we're really, really
careful, we might be able to come up
with new ways to train generative models that
actually avoid right, avoid
or are resilient to these
you know, gradations like, we
have with collapse.
But the key is that we need to exploit, right,
the signal that is hidden,
right, in this collapse
sequence, and turn that into,
you know, some new new way of of training.
Right? So we saw neon as this one
kind of scratches the surface. Of
one potential way and I and I
think that the key thing is that that that
Neon opens the door to really thinking about not
just model collapse and
madness, but also really how we can be
more data efficient. Right? With
the data sets that we that we do have. Right?
For example, if you have trained
you know, I don't see why anybody wouldn't take any
model that they are using today and
just take another 1%
of compute and improve the
FID of of your model. Okay?
But there's still, you know, lots of open questions.
We're thinking about other people in the community
are thinking about this
this neon represents just one
way of creating, you know, bad
signals. That you can use to tune your
models. There's a whole cottage
industry of folks that are thinking of
of either damaging models
or damaging signals.
In order to improve
the performance of generative modeling.
Is there a way to somehow do this optimally?
Right? So get this optimal bad
direction right, that when we flip
it becomes a really, really good
direction. Also need to
understand this this prophylactic aspect
meaning the fact that some of these methods that folks
have actually can tolerate
some amount of synthetic data, even
in their, what they think is their real
training data. This is, I I think, a
really big open open problem.
And then and then finally, know, we
have just focused on
generation as our ultimate task.
But you know, there's a whole host of other
machine learning tasks that folks would like to
use models for. And and is
really unexcited is
and and madness actually impacts
those kind of setups. Okay.
Well, with that, I will end and say thanks
very much for the invitation to be here.
And happy to answer any questions. Thank
you.
Thank you, Rich. We have a few minutes
for questions. If if anybody has
questions, you can go to the middle.
Yeah. Thank
you very much for the interesting talk. I'm just wondering,
can you give some very intuitive way
to understand why the gradient due
to synthetic data like, anti
align with the real gradient?
Because that sounds really counterintuitive to
me. Because if you think of human as
a, like, society of learning machines,
it seems that I need
to tend to disagree
with what ancient sense say.
Like, for the benefit of, like, human,
like, developing? So
but that's not what I do. So, like,
I found it really counterintuitive.
Yeah. It it it is counterintuitive, and
it really surprised us I think it's
easier to think about it in distribution space
than in parameters. Space. So think
in like score function,
space and then just remember that in neon,
it's just like the first order
first order term in a Taylor series.
Basically, if you take do Taylor series, the distribution.
Basically, what happens when you when
you do a mode seeking sampler, is
that you are basically pushing
down the tails Right? As I said, you're pushing
down the tails of the distribution.
And and pumping up the the the
peaks or the mode of the distribution.
And so and so basically, this
this direction away right,
direction away, basically
tells you right, the direction
that you that you need to go to
push those to push the
tails down and to push the
mode up. And so basically,
reversing that direction basically
corrects. Right? Debias is
basically. The distribution.
And then if you just think that's basically how Sims
works, And then if you think about
if you think about with neon,
basically, you take this argument that I just talked
about in distribution space, you do tailor
series, The thetas, the
parameters of the first order terms,
And then there are second order terms that are determined
by how good the model was
in the first place, second order and higher order
terms, and you it's easy to show
that if the model was good enough to
start with, meaning close enough to
the trueest data distribution, you can show
that the first order terms dominate the
higher order terms, and you can just basically
do this parameter merge. So
so hopefully that hopefully that helps.
I see. A kind of more philosophical question.
Do you think we should, like, disagree with
other people more? Like, think your work suggest
that? I would agree.
Certainly, in certainly in like
dialogue and online dialogue. Right? The
you know, another related
idea here that goes way back is the idea of echo
chambers. Right? Which is
a human human idea.
That that that people proposed. As soon as social
media came out, people were like, uh-oh.
We're gonna end up having echo chambers where people
have, say, certain political ideas or
people who love Taylor Swift right,
and don't like Madonna, gonna hang
out and their their ideas are gonna be
biases are gonna be reinforced.
You can really think of model collapse
and
as an echo chamber of AI.
So, yes, you should disagree
with people as much as you can. Very
interesting. Thanks.
Just a quick question. So w
is the hyperparameter
Yeah. W is a hyper I should have mentioned. Just a hyper
parameter that you could search for
using some kind of, say, grid search. Okay.
But, maybe
can you give some I mean, theoretically,
I mean, it should depends on
the number of Yeah. Very good, but
yeah. So there's a hyperparameter
hyperparameter w.
That determines performance.
We have rules of thumb, but no theory as
of yet. That that's that's a good question.
That's an open yeah, open scientific
question. Thank you.
Alright. For this
oh, maybe okay. Let's take one more question, Adan.
Thank you for a great talk. I have a
question. Is it true
that you have added this
synthetic synthetic data
that was generated from the same model
throughout the training loop. Correct. In
the in this method, in
neon, it's the exact same model.
So have you tried adding,
the data from the different model? Great question.
So the question is, what about
using synthetic data from a different
model? It's kind of like a transfer learning
kind of thing. It also
works. Also works. Not quite as
well, and I think you could see
that if, you know, if you really rely on this, like,
degradation signal hypothesis,
then the the no better model than
the very very model you have. Yeah, it
transfers really quite well. Okay. Thank you so
much. Question. Alright.
Let's, thank Rich. We have another
round of applause. Thank
you.
So our next speaker is
Matthew Viar. He's a
professor of physics, at John Hopkins
and EPFL University and
more recently, he has focused his research
on understanding how deep learnings
work, in particular, his
lab made very interesting contribution
to how compositional and hierarchical structures
in data help the learning
process. So today,
we're gonna hear
about some of the results in the context of language
models.
Now you can hear me. Yeah.
So, so I'm very happy to be here. Thanks
in Rio. Thanks for having us, and
it's a beautiful workshop. So it's great.
And I'm also very excited to tell you about
this work. Because I think it's engaging
with the fact that's impacting all of
us, namely neural scanning laws,
so so the idea that if you put
more money, more parameters,
more data, you can, in a sort of predictive manner,
increase the performance of,
LLMs. Which has completely,
you know, impacted the field and led
tech companies to those massive investments
that, you know, we're witnessing
the the change of technology. And
despite that, for for theory, we really have
no clue what's to, you know, what controls
those I think Bruno nicely
summarized it this morning. You have
lots of very beautiful theory on kernel methods
and so on, I which
in in some cases can be very useful, but
my contention is that for languages, it's
not really a good way to think about it. And what
we are trying to propose here is actually
a theory where you would be predictive.
Predict the exponent based on the statistics
of languages. And this is the work
that's done with very talented
young collaborators, Francesco
Cagneta and Allan Raventos. And in collaboration,
with the group. Of Surya,
in Stanford.
So the general question,
no.
Is about learning, you know, language from
exam. And it's an old question
for for linguists. And the question
really here is what they call creativity.
If, you know, a child is exposed to sentences,
how many sentences does he need to
be able to create new
sentences that it never heard before,
that will be correct grammatically.
And And, Ram Shamsky, last century,
you know, famously said that it may be
impossible. That you need grammar needs to be innate.
And what I find very exciting is that with
LLMs okay. Now we we see that they
can amazingly well.
So it's possible. But you can
really you know, it offers new handle
to to study important questions
like, you know, what are actually the statistical
correlation. That are harvested by those
LLMs? How many data do you need to learn
what?
Okay. So we know, what's the one
objective that works to learn languages, and
you you guys all know about next token prediction,
but I I will still have this slide to introduce
some some key concepts.
So you use the chain rule. So
t will be the maximal context.
Let's say, the size of a paragraph or something like
that. X I would be token
in position I. And what you
use is the fact that the joint probability can
be written as its product p
of x, you know, p of x one, p of x two
knowing x one, and so on.
So note that
are my notation for context between one
and token n minus one.
And then what you do is you train a model,
say, a large language model, to maximize
the likelihood of your observation. So when you
take the log of this product, you get a
sum a sum of
loss l, sum
of l n, and l n is the
loss associated with a a context
of size n that vary between one and t.
So this quantity l n will be very important
here. And the other thing
you need to know is that this cross entropy,
even if you have the best it
it cannot go to zero.
At best, it can go to the conditional
entropy, which I will call h n.
So conditional entropy of the next token
if you know n tokens before.
That's, again, going to be very important
here. Okay.
So what we have to learn then is this
probability, conditional probability of x
n if you know the context before.
But here comes a very common, you know, curse
of dimensionality problems that if you are
trying to histogram this distribution,
it would be essentially impossible because the number
of you know, context
of size and growth
So it should be impossible
to do generically, and it is for unstructured
data. So it means that
learnable data have a lot of structure. So what is
you know, the structure of language that makes it
learnable And how is it are
vested by, say, large language models?
So one aspect that many
people believe is actually key, and that's the name
of this conference, right, it's representation learning.
And in particular, the fact that it's also true
for CNN and images, but that those
net, as they learn what
in physics or physicists in the audience, we
will call coarse grain file So if we
describe a liquid, we're not we
it's not useful to track all the position
and velocity of particles. Whether
you want to have fields like pressure, velocity,
and things like that. So
you build variables that do not depend on
details. And,
deep nets and
So here, I like to give the example in LLMs,
this golden gate bridge
what you see that you have linear combination
of neurons that
respond very specifically to having
the notion of golden gate in the
sense. But this is very robust.
It does not depend on the details of
the syntax of the sentence.
It even doesn't depend if it was a, you know, multilinguage
model. If it's said in Chinese or said
in English, and if
it's a multi model, you also have vision.
If you show a picture of the Golden
Gate, you trigger the same linear set of
of neurons. So that's also
a question. You know? How do you actually
build those coarse grain variables
What structure in the data enables
it?
Okay. So then that leads to how do you actually
quantify success in
those neural scanning laws? And in this
talk, I will just talk about one of them,
which has to do with how your
performance, your test loss
depend on the number of data
If you have lots of compute and lots of
parameters. Your data are limited.
So the tesla goes like b to
some exponent alpha. Okay. So
that's my question. What controls
this alpha?
So Okay. So this talk is cut
into two So the first part
of the talk for the physicists, it's like thermodynamics.
I will make a sort of simple assumption
and from it, we'll be able to
make predictions that we can actually test
natural languages. But this
this assumption is simple to state, but why it's
true is not obvious. So in
the second part of the talk, I will actually talk
about a microscopic model where we
can understand why this
assumption is actually correct.
So So let me introduce the two,
what I will argue are the two key
properties of natural languages that control their
the neural scaling load. And the first
one is the fact that you
have long range correlation between words
or token in text. Which is well
known for for a long time. So,
for example, you can define this
matrix, you know, if I have token, mu, what is the probability
that I see token new
at a distance n. I
it's a matrix that depends on the number
of token but you can look
at norms of this matrix. And whatever
norm you look, operator norm, forbidden use, you find
the same result. And
here, it's shown for the two data sets that we're going
to study, tiny stories, which are
sort of fairy tales.
And WikiTek, which is a curated version of
Wikipedia. And what you find
in both cases is that you have
poor low decay of those correlation.
And for Wikitext, it sort of breakdown
after 30 or 40 tokens.
And this is actually the scale that I
consider. Which is a few sentences.
And that's where we can test our theory.
So you can measure those exponent, and you find
that the depend on the dataset, and I call
this exponent beta. How's the correlation
decrease with context? N?
So that's the first key quantity. And
from it, we can extract an important
notion which is if you
give me a given training set of size
so in this talk p the size of
the training set, on which
context length can you actually
measure correlation.
And that's what you see in this simple example.
So that's okay, that's for Shakespeare data,
and you see the polo correlation in Shakespeare.
In color, you see you know, trying
to measure those correlation with more and more
data. And if you don't have much data, you do very
And you see visually that there is a scale.
And this scale is readily obtained by
just comparing sampling noise going like one over
of peak. And the signal I told
you about that goes, like, n power minus beta.
And from that, you get a scale. We call it
n star of p It depends
on the size of of the training set. It
tells you on which scale you can actually measure correlation.
And so here come our key assumption.
Our key assumption will be
that machines they cannot exploit
context that are much larger than this
NSA star of p. But
if you have very good machines like LLMs,
and not kernels, they can
do they can work essentially
optimally on that scale. What I mean
by optimally will be stated
in the coming slide.
So the second property we argue is very
important is this conditional entropy.
That I told you about. Right? What is
the entropy of a token if I know n tokens just
before? And And
it seems that it's very hard to measure because again,
it's cursed by dimensionality. Here we're going to
use that LLMs and do not seem to be cursed
by dimensionality. So in particular,
we will use the fact that
I told you already that this
conditional entropy
has to be the optimal of l n,
if you give me a machine which has a huge capacity,
so let's take the capacity to
infinity first, And then you train
on a huge number of data, and you are
fixing the context end.
Then this loss l n should converge. And
what it should converge to is precisely
this And that's
something that you can actually test and
perform empirically.
And that's what you show in all those plots.
So this is l n. This,
this loss for a contact end. So
the effective is n
and the different colors what happens
when you increase your training set.
And what you find is that if you are at small
n Zoosk curve actually
converge to a well defined value. And
so it should be our conditional entropy.
And then we double check
that this limit actually does not depend on the
architecture that you use. So
if you use GPT style, you know, LLM
or Lamma, or even if you look state
model like Mamba, you actually
find the same value. And
what you find, again, on the scale of
30, 50 tokens, is that
this conditional entropy is well fitted by
a power low decay with some exponents
that depend on the training set,
but you that you can measure.
And so here's a theory slide
I our assumption that
you can perform optimally for deep
architecture on that scale
means that the test loss, if you give me you know,
if you have a very large contact t
t, but you give me a finite training set, you
will only be able to
as a language on this context n star
of p. If you do it optimally,
then your tesla should be given by this
conditional entropy on that scale. And
the good thing about this theory is that it's very predictive,
because n star of p
you know how it behaves.
And the entropy goes like n minus gap.
Gamma. So you immediately get that your
neural scanning logs alpha
should behave like gamma over two b. Beta.
There's another prediction that think
leads to even much more stringent prediction.
Which is very common
in physics, but maybe less
usual in other fields. It's called scaling collapse. The
fact that a function of two variables like
this test loss that depends on the context
and and also on the training set p, is really
a function of one variable in this guy.
So comes from the fact that it it has to
have two asymptotic behaviors and a
crossover between them.
So imagine that, you look at
the case where your data the number
of data is small. Then
what will happen is that the context and
not matter. You see effective context on which you
can harvest data is n star of p,
which is much smaller. And
therefore, you recover that the test loss
should just depends on this h of
star of p, which is p minus alpha.
On the other hand, if you have lots of
data for finite context, at
some point, this data n star of
p becomes larger than n, but there's no
no data to explore on larger
context. So you will just saturate performance at
the entropy and context end, which is
just n point for minus gamma.
So what you get ultimately by putting
this together is that your test loss, that's
a function of two variables, should really
be a power of n time what we call a
scaling function. Something that only depends
on on this ratio here.
That behaves as a constant
for very large p and as a parallel
for small argument.
Okay. Now comes empirical test.
So the the first prediction is just predicting
the
and, okay, the scale at which we we we
work we are in the data limited
regime, so we have things like 1,000,000,000
parameters, 10 per eight, a few 10
per eight data.
So number of data is actually seen on the
x axis here.
And what you see in color
is essentially the classical polo. How
does it test loss
set? And what you see as
the dotted line, our prediction
without fitting permit. This has
no fitting parameter. We measure those two
exponents gamma and beta. We deduce
what alpha should be. And you find
that for Wikitext, it works
remarkably well. And for tiny stories, it
works pretty well. Actually, as you increase
the maximal horizon t, the maximal context
t seems to work better and better.
But what's really think, is
most convincing is this non trivial
prediction of scaling collapse. So here, what you
see is those test loss l n on
context n as a function of the size of the training
set b. So the different curves
corresponds to different colors
which corresponds to different end.
And that's where our theory makes a very
stringent prediction. If we rescale the
axis, in a way that's not fitting
parameter, it's completely fixed by
previous measurement. All those curves
should collapse. And they do.
They do both for tiny story and
for Text. So I
think that's the strongest support that we are on the
good track.
Okay. So, now comes the microscopic
theory because the is,
why does this assumption is actually correct?
Why is it that you know, once you
start to measure correlation, you do essentially
optimally? It means that you beat the curse of
dimensionality. So
what's going on?
So what is the mechanism whereby
machines do well on that scale?
And for which data structure is it possible?
Because for generic data, it's not possible. You're cursed
by dimension. So
Okay. So the game we are playing as physicists
is to think about synthetic
models of languages. We're inspired by the work
of linguists I mean, Norems Shamsky in particular.
And they have you know, the notion that
underlying the linear structure of text
you have trees. I mean, that's a very old idea, much
older than I'm sure.
And then that you can describe
the statistics of text by describing
the statistic whereby latent variable
that you don't observe on that tree
can give rise to strings of latent
variables. That's context free grammar.
So we'll be playing with models of context free
grammar, and it's an idea that has been
also very impactful for computer vision
It's called pattern theory. It's the fact that
underlying images, you also have trees. And
images of a grammar on their of their
own. So
there have been works, you know, looking at how
LLMs learn context free grammar,
But who's works considered complicated
context free grammar where learning could not
be understood, Postmortem
analysis of the algorithm done was studied.
So here, we want to make it simple, and we are actually
going to use in conjunction
two approximations that we have proposed in some literature.
So first one, our tree will have
a frozen regular topology.
The second one is that production rules
how one latent give rise to a string
are going to be random.
And if you do those two
ingredients, then you can compute
all correlations in this problem.
And really understand how and test your
ideas of how LLMs learn learn
such models. Okay.
So we call it the random hierarchy
model. So it's a context free grammar.
The key ingredient is that
my mouse here? Yes. So each
symbol here give rise to strings.
So let's call s. The size of
the string. What's really important is
that, say, b can give rise to d f,
but also to other strings.
In this model, the parameters that control that
is m. So b could lead to m
different strings, And those strings, we call
them synonyms. Because they all mean
big How
do we choose those strings? Well, we
choose them randomly. That's the point.
And we also choose them
as
set that have, no overlap.
So say a and b cannot give
rise to the same stream.
There's another interesting
quantity in a model like that, It's
a fraction f of the rules that are used.
For example, d f exist as
a string. But many strings
do not exist. And this fraction f
depends on the vocabulary size. And
we can manipulate a
model like that essentially is compositional, so
you see you don't see the latent
visible at the end. And it
can generate it's a language that can generate
an immense number of data exponential in the
context, the maximal context end.
And so you can study what we study
at the time was last token prediction.
What happens for a machine that's
trying to predict the last token knowing
what comes before.
Okay. And so the first point I want to make is
that simple model like that captures the
two key properties I told you about in languages.
And again, the first one is well known.
It's well known that if you have tree like models
like that, they lead to poor
correlation, poor low correlations,
of symbols at the bottom.
Essentially, what happens
is that every time you move
along this tree, you can ask how to
variables visible or not are correlated in a tree
like that. Every time you move along the
tree, you the correlation diminishes
by a quantity that just depends on m.
This number of synonyms.
And so correlation decay
exponentially with the distance on the tree,
but the distance real token
space is also
the tree. And at the end, it leads to a
correlation that decrease as a ball of distance.
So you would have to trust me on that. This is
which can be controlled. It's not
universal. It just depend on m, the number of
synonyms, and as the branching ratio
of the stream.
Okay. So it has polar correlation. It
also has a conditional entropy that's
And so so you ask, what is the entropy of this
last token that you don't see here?
If I condition to knowing everything that
comes before? And what
happens is that you don't really
doesn't really matter everything what comes before. The
only thing that matters are actually those latent
variables that I surrounded by
green. Only them are informative
in terms of what can happen for the
hidden So And what
happens is that at every level you consider
the fact, for example, that you've seen a,
restrict the number of you know,
symbols that are actually here, written as
b, by a factor f, you
know, the fraction of rules that
And at every level you consider
you always have this factor f entering
here. And so what you find
is that the entropy as a function of
context is just f to the power l,
the and of the tree. I mean, there is a floor.
I'm not going to enter into details.
And that's just again, the distance
add along the tree being, you know,
logarithmic in the context length
you get a power load. So
in this model, it's correct that the conditional
entropy is a power law of con
Again, with an exponent that you can
manipulate at hand.
So Okay. And in this model, we can
really understand what
is the mechanism leads to learning.
Why is it that our main assumption in the first pack
part of the talk is actually correct?
So So, again, what you're trying to understand
is a correlation between a long engram
and the last token. And, again,
it should be cursed by dimensionality because
the number of engrams is immense. You never see
twice the same. If n is large.
What's actually saving you in a model like that is
that you don't, again, care about the end gram, you just care
about those those green latent
variables that I surrounded
here. So, if your machine can
learn to build those latent variables,
then you're saved.
And actually, you can learn them
precisely because those latent variable
controls the correlation. So, for example,
imagine that you're looking at the correlation between
this string h g and the last
token. Those correlation
only depend on the latent d above.
Synonyms have the same correlation.
And so it means if you give me enough data, I
can measure those correlation
It's a signal to noise argument.
And cluster together those you know,
those strengths into latent variables.
And I can do it hierarchically. If I know that this
is e and this is f, I can again look
at correlation between those latent
variable and the last token and
build those latent hierarchy
So it's hierarchical cluster.
So that's a mechanism to actually build
those latent variables that
are cause during variables. They do not depend on
details on what were the exact production
rules. Behind them.
So Okay. So in a model like
that,
what happens is that if you do
next token prediction, you start
to learn this production rule from the bottom.
So you first learn production rules that are close
to the last token and that are at the
bottom of the tree. And as you give
more and more data, you start to learn
higher and higher level variables
in and you and further and
further away. And, actually,
the bottleneck in a model like that is
to cluster together
synonyms that are the furthest away from
you. And what
really matters is a correlation
between strings and token in a model like that.
But in those models, it's scales in the
same way as a token token correlation.
Third, the end, what you find is that this
assumptions is the
fact that when you have enough data
to resolve correlation, that's when you can
actually completely learn the model. Is true.
For the simple models of context figure.
Okay. So, actually,
that's something that you can
test in those synthetic languages. You
can vary parameters and
what I told you before is the fact that we
have predict prediction for neural scanning loss
for this exponent. Alpha, and it
should depend on the parameters of the model.
And so that's what we test here.
M is the number of synonyms. VISO, I did
introduce it. It's the size of the vocabulary.
Taken to be the same at every level.
And what you can compare our observation
what our scaling loads on an LLM
trying to learn the synthetic languages.
Compare compared with, you know,
theoretical
Okay. So,
so here are my conclusion slide.
So what we propose is a theory of neural scanning
laws that relate the scanning
laws to the exponent to actually
properties of natural languages that you can measure.
I told you that there are two key properties
token token correlation and this conditional entropy.
On context length. N.
And that these proper properties appear naturally
in contact in simple context free grammar
models. And that leads to
a mechanism for this hierarchical
for for building coarse grain variable, which is
based on the sort of hierarchical clustering
approach. So
okay. So if I have two minutes, we were
also asked to to give some some vision of
where it's going. And,
and I just wanted to mention, in
addition to you know, what was discussed
this morning in terms of why is it that
interpretability understanding really
what LLMs are doing is
important. I see
and I completely agree with what was said, but I
see another another
argument for that. Is
the connection between what LLMs, how
they are representing languages.
And how our brand are representing language.
And the as time goes,
there are there is more and more evidence that
those two representation are
closely related. So I think that
once when you do theories of how LLMs,
you know, represent language,
you're also doing neuroscience,
at a brain level where there is very little
theory done, but, where there are more and
more facts. So so
I think this is a very,
you know, interesting field
for the future. And,
and how and I didn't connect that to my
talk, but something that I find very interesting is
that example,
when they map LLMs to
brains, they find that as you train better
LLMs, you start
to map better at you
know, low levels aspect of the
cortex, like auditory cortex, for example.
Is and you train more and more this
mapping starts to occur at more
and more abstract level. And even
the simple models I told you about, it's
also true. If you give me more and more data, you
learn rules
Okay. Thank you.
Alright. Yeah. Use the microphone in
the middle if for questions.
Thank you very much for the talk. To
me, it's really exciting to see the universality
curve I mean, the function f that everything
collapses to in the first part of our talk,
But, you know, in physics, that usually happens
near phase transitions, or at least there needs to
be some CFT I mean,
any, like, scale invariant theory
So, like, do you think there's some
kind of scale invariant theory or a phase transition
like, it seems that language is happening
near this kind of place. Well, I I would think
that, this sort of
scaling collapse here
also occurs in those
simple models of language, artificial ones
that I told you about. Uh-huh. Uh-huh. And
and it's so it's also true in this class of model,
but the physics of it is a bit different from crude
usual critical phenomena. Where
you can have local interactions that
that's temperature
lead to, you know,
polo correlations. Uh-huh. You need fine
tuning in physics to see polo correlation.
But in data, languages,
you see it all the time. You do have
you know, parallel correlation of tokens or words.
So I think the, you know, I don't think it's because
the world is fine tuned to be critical. I
think it's because you have another rational for
that, and I think the understanding that you
have underlying text street.
So but still, if you think
about three at this level, you still have the
scaling collabs that emerge.
Thank you.
Thank you. There any
other questions?
Alright. So
we have an half an hour break. You can
and both Rich and Matthew are in the
the space if you have questions to talk to them. And
then after this half an hour, we're
gonna have the panel discussion at three
So, let's thank Matthew
with another round of applause.
Yeah. And if you are presenting your poster in the later
poster session, use the break to hang
it up here
come take your seats. And
for five of you, those seats are on stage.
You know who you are. I'm
with you. See you.
First time I got
Alright.
I you guys ready?
We would
Yeah. Alright.
Alright. Everybody, thanks for sticking around for the panel.
I'm Jamie. One of the organizers here.
Yeah. Honestly, really loved all the all five
talks we had, and I'm jazzed
to have this panel here in particular
to ask questions
to because I mean, as we saw from the talks,
I all these five
researchers have
like, well developed, but very distinct research
team. Tastes. Different approaches
to developing a science of deep learning,
that I I think are are are all
complementary and and really inspiring. And I'm I'm, you know,
excited to explore this. So
this will be a panel gonna run for like
an hour ish. Towards the end, we'll
have audience questions, so you can have, you know, have questions
germinating, they can come out at the end.
Alright. So, and for anyone
who wasn't here for the talks, the the,
panelists here are, David Bauer, Julia
Kemp, Rich Berniak.
And Matthew Vaiart and Jeremy
Cohen. Alright.
So, first question,
we're gonna start with an easy one.
In our field, what makes good science?
So, yeah. Like, you
know, we all we all want to understand this
We all want to understand deep learning
we want some kind of a scientific theory of
And clearly, there are ways
to there there are attempts to make progress,
avenues progress that that
that seem to be working, that are more promising than others.
Like, what makes good science? What do you look for?
In a paper? What makes you excited about a new result?
I mean, the goal is to get at the truth. Right? So,
like, like good science is
what's true. I think that's
more important than anything else.
I mean, some ways that you can tell that it it sort
of possible to, like, fool
oneself into, like, thinking that, like,
like, you found the truth when you haven't. And so I guess
that's there are other, like, signatures of like
good science. But, like, know,
like, which I mean, there are
probably a lot, but, like, just to name one
like, one sanity check that you you're on the right path is
when you can for example, like, if can make like predictions,
like in Matthew's talk, like, showing, like, the
model, like, makes this precise prediction.
That's, like, you know, an like
like something has gotta be going right for that
to be true. So that's a good signature.
Hello?
So I would just be repeating what actually you said
this morning, which resonated with
me that good science has, many forms.
And, and if you think about,
you know, what you were introducing,
how do we a good paper should it
have the theory and the algorithms that
works in practice and and I
think, no, it's much more of a continuum
where, you want to have theory and practice that
two ends of a continuum and, and
we work as a community to to make it
work. So so very good work can
can be there at, very different location
in this continuum.
And also with different methodologies
It could be, as you said, theorem, is
one approach, but but there's
another way to try to be rigorous, which
is maybe it's not your aim. You propose
arguments, but then you have to be very rigorous in
terms of how you actually test it
So I think that's already that's also
very variable, and it a
it would be very nice that, yeah, all those, you know,
all those different approaches are
considered and
Yes. I'll just add
there's a
theory of science Right? So, we would like any
deep learning theories to to
basically, hew to those
proper basically properties like you'd ideally
like to be able to have hypotheses
that are falsifiable
and ideas like that. I think the
thing that I look for most
that I think was in that
it should be actionable
and that's just because we are
a we are a small little
tribe in a very big
machine learning world.
Most folks who come to ICLR
are not. Here for
the theory. Right? They're here for the
benchmarks. Right? And so I
think the more that you're theory can
can be actionable by people who are
chasing those benchmarks, the more that it's
likely to be,
have an impact on the
field. Michael, for this
Yes. So, to add
to what my colleagues
have said,
I see I see two pieces to
science. Right? There is the understanding science
and then there is the nice
part where we can actually
as you say, be actionable or predict something.
Right? And, I feel both
pieces are very important and often I think
a bonus that you get when you do
the understanding pieces that often something
actionable actually comes out. Right? And
that very nice. I do see,
a bit of a tendency, so I'm not you know, if
you steep in the science community more,
there is a bit of a tendency maybe to
do the science because we can.
We are able to compute on Gaussians,
Let's just put a Gaussian on the data.
So that's a temptation that I I I feel
in my science colleagues, and
there it is, I think, important to ask, you know,
am I actually modeling the
truth or the phenomenon I want to explain.
Right? So and and this is an important
you need to not just do it because you can.
Think. Right? You better,
do it because it will explain something.
So as the last person, I I don't have much
to add. You know,
science should be rigorous, should be actionable.
I I think I I tend to advise
my students to think
about ideas that might
be productive. That might
be good building blocks that you could build other
ideas on top of, I think that's in addition
to all the things that that are talked about here.
But there's a human aspect
to to what makes good science.
So okay. I I I there's a question I wanna
I wanna piggyback on that before I get
to the next one which is all of us in
this room, I'm sure, have felt
precisely the pressure that that Richard is pointing out
That in order to be relevant to
the people outside of the room,
you know, we we we better help them beat
soda. And
and, like, great if we do,
but Jeremy says something in his
talk that that spoke to me and I'm sure to others,
that, like, we can't always
you can't always do that in one step. So so so
yeah. Sorry. I I wonder how you guys
resolve this for yourselves and what advice you would
give to, like, students
who are who are trying to do something relevant, trying to
get conference papers in, you know,
how do you manage this this these two tensions?
And and what's what's philosophy?
Yeah. Good question. Yeah. So I think I
would probably like, tend to,
have dis I I would maybe disagree with
the the the argument that we should
try very hard to be
like, to make give actionable
guidance for practitioners. Because
I think that, like, I feel like we're
just in a
deep learning we don't understand deep learning very well.
And like most of the time, you just can't I feel like the set
of things that we can currently give
actionable guidance on is minuscule
relative to the set of things that we will hopefully
one day be able to give actionable guidance
on. So I think it's better to, like, not
there is pressure, and I think there's a vicious cycle.
I think there's the following vicious cycle where, like,
theorists like, see
talk to practitioners and realize that practitioners
don't care about theory. And then
they were like, okay, I need to make my
theory more relevant to practitioners. But then the
practitioners in turn, what they do is they read
these and then they implement
it. And it doesn't work as well as
their baseline. And then they're
like, oh, theory doesn't work. I think
there's like a vicious cycle here where, like,
I think that I think what I would
sort of recommend is,
like, just saying to the practitioners, like,
sorry, like, I
Like, and just sort of viewers
just sort of sticking to their guns more. I'm
using theorists in the broadest sense of the term, like
people who work on understanding singing to their guns and saying
like we're gonna do the theory and then when the theory is done
then it'll be useful.
If you if you are looking at other sciences
like physics, I mean, and would not have
published anything and and still yet,
you know, this giant technological impact
at the end, but,
but again, I think we work as a community.
And and the same person doesn't need to go from
very big ideas to to
application. So I,
I would completely agree with that. Yeah.
Yeah. I don't have much to add except you can
always point out the success stories. Right?
Okay. So theorists think, they do their thing, and
then we get things like resonance.
Which you might argue maybe comes from petitioner, but
maybe it comes from trying to understand why the
gradients remember, this whole thing in 2016,
gradients explode gradients shrink, everybody
thinks about it. Boom. ResNet comes. Right? So,
clearly, it's a success. So I think,
even practitioners will, I think,
admit that theorists diffusion models.
I mean, come on. Right? So I
think there's enough success stories to
have a justification for our slow
approach. Right? Not on a three month deadline.
Sure. I I wanna add another thing, which is so
in May and maybe my my area is a
little a little different, but even
encouraged the theorists
to think this way. Which
is that
one of the things that we can do when
we're looking at fundamental questions
is also open up the space
of new applications, new problems
that you can solve that people didn't think. So maybe diffusion models
is one of them. Right? But new problems
to solve that people didn't think
was what they were trying to do, but if you take a
new look at it, closer
to my area, there's this area
of model
where you have a model and maybe you understand
the structure well enough that without
process, process, you can customize
it in different ways.
And, and and because of
different properties that the distribution has or
different things. Right? And
and, and it actually became this
of practical techniques
if you go to Hugging Face
I think something like third of
all the models on Hugging Face
are customized models that use some of these
lightweight techniques
that came out of like, a mechanistic
understanding of what what's going on.
But it's not it's not
something we get credit for, like, moving
state of the art forward. It's a new
application. Something different. But I still think
I I still think it was a really substantial
contribution. To open it up. So
you know,
So
so so one
of the most exciting things about this this science
that we're that we're in that we're hopefully
building is it's really nascent.
It's not it's not clear what
this theory we're gonna find is.
It's not clear what the understanding will look like
or or, what it'll
be useful for. And that that's wonderful, and
I I think it inspires me people here.
So so I'm I'm curious to hear your answers to the
question of well, what are we what are
we trying to do here? Right? Because
like clearly,
not everything is the science of deep learning.
The boundaries are really vague.
The the the goals are the goals are really big.
And, like, if you were to
articulate maybe,
you know, in a way, again, trying to, like, inspire
a young graduate is or something to get interested in this,
like, what what are we trying to
do here? And and and, like,
what are what are the highest ambitions? What are the scopes?
And what should we be aiming for and, like, work
backwards to decide what to do today?
Yeah. I guess my answer is maybe I
think not everybody would agree with this answer.
But I guess to me,
like, and this might appear
to contradict what I said last on the last question,
but it doesn't actually. To me,
the the ultimate goal of deep
learning theory should be to drive practice. That's
the end goal. The end goal is that when
people are doing deep learning,
that they are talking about theory. They are using theory
to guide what they do. Maybe it's not
gonna tell them oh, set the learning
rate to like point o four
two. Like like, it's not gonna like,
necessarily tell them exactly what to do but they're gonna
they're gonna, they're gonna, they're gonna, they're gonna, they're gonna, they're gonna, they're gonna, they're gonna it should be
valuable enough that they naturally find themselves using
it. When they go about
doing their deep learning. But, like, that's
the long term goal. To get there,
we first need to build the theory that's capable
of doing that. I think a not
a different a totally different answer would be like, oh, the point of
theory is to
like, understand. But like to me
like understanding is kind of ill defined
goal. And like,
it's whereas like,
like, like it it's not
even clear It's not act
like it's not actionable. How do you know if you've how do you even
measure it? You've under So like
the the me the ultimate goal is to be driving
practice. But to get there now,
need to focus on
building the foundations first.
So in terms of understanding not being
clear, I guess, if you just state it like that, yes, but
then you can if you try
to clarify the question and ask, for example,
I mean, that's very subjective. What questions
are driving you? I inform
you one question I'm fascinated about is an old
question. You know, generic data are not learnable.
What in the structure of data make them learnable?
And why is it that deep net are actually really good at
it. You know? So so I think it's
once you make the quest question
specific and your five drive toward them, then
then I think you can this notion of
understanding become meaningful.
In addition to those kinds of question,
one aspect that I find very fascinating
is Now, I mean,
this and relating to the works that,
I mean, some of, people
here are really working on, like, interpretability,
how syntax, semantic are represented
in, language models. I was starting
to mention that in
in the talk, but, if you
you know, if you do theory on trying to I
mean, of all, it's a fundamental question in itself.
How can a machine learn to speak? How
does it generate, you know, good
language? And I think linguists are fascinated
by that even if it was just a machine.
But then now we are finding more and more evidence that
representation in the brain are similar
to the machine like Lina. Last month, there was
a paper showing that
king minus man plus woman is queen. That's
is is when known already in World two vec.
Actually, it's also there in our brain. I
mean, so so I think
it's another justification that if we understand is
not
machine specific. So it's not
just about understanding what specific man machine,
it's something of nature. So I think,
I think I forgot the question.
Because I was thinking about these great answers.
And and just thinking where's
my t shirt? Just
so disappointed that I have a t
shirt. I'm a medium.
So so I'm not sure if I'm not sure
if this addresses the question, but,
maybe it addresses the the previous question.
But I I think it's important
like really important to like keep
in your mind, like differentiate between
what I would call, like, a theory
driven field and an
an example of a theory driven field is
communication Everybody has a
phone, Right?
Five g, six g, seven g's
next. This field is
is just built wholeheartedly on
on information theory. Right? Which is
rigorous branch of mathematics. And and
the important thing is in a field like that, understanding
can be total.
Like, and and people are building systems
that are within epsilon of, like,
Shannon capacity. Right?
So theory and practice
can really really go together. And I think
some people come into the theory of
deep learning world thinking that it's
a little bit like that, when I would argue it is
much more like chemistry
or neuroscience. Right? Where you'd have
this incredible complexity
where understanding really may never
be truly reached
may never be truly reached but
that's not just a that's not necessarily
bad. That's like means there's just tremendous
opportunity for a light like
a lifetime of work. And so
to me, I think folks who
work in deep learning theory, it's really about, like,
joining into that that that
journey.
Yeah. So I don't have that much to add, but
also there is a difference, I
think, between science of deep learning and
theory of deep learning. I don't know. Also, I don't remember
what you asked. And I already got my t shirt. Thank
you. But,
it's different. And I think for us, it is important
to bring the scientific method
to this field. Right? Because indeed
there is all these other rooms that are chasing the
benchmarks, and perhaps,
you know, are neither motivated nor
set to apply the scientific method, which also
is about admitting you know, what fails,
basically, which is not so popular in the
other rooms. And I think
this is you know, as a scientist, that's what we have
do, scientific method, write down what works,
write down what fails, understand failure
modes is one important thing, and,
this is also upon us as
a community of scientists in this field
to do, I think.
So I I I think that
I I like this question a lot. I think that
I I like the sentiment.
Yes. Well, you know, or or something like that. I I've been
mostly thinking that, the the
actually, the organizers are amazing
because unlike any other workshop I've seen, they
seem to have ads as well. And so
I'm I'm wondering where these ads come from.
So
but but,
the the
so I'm gonna echo
one of the sentiments that I think I it
resonates with me
you know, we are we're in a messy field.
But we are also in an ancient field.
Because the question of
what is thinking
is as old as philosophy. It's
a 5,000 year old question.
And and we are at this unique
moment when suddenly,
we can analyze the question of
what is thinking what is learning, what is
reasoning, what is cognition, in a
new way that that
the old philosophers could only dream of. There's there's
this old treasure chest
of questions that used to be non scientific
And yes, they're very messy, messy
questions. Know, what is language? You
know, what is what is intent?
What is agency? You
know, what is meaning, what
is belief, Right?
They're messy, messy questions that used to
be philosophical almost religious questions.
But actually because now we
have reproducible
system, mathematical systems that exhibit a
lot of these behaviors. We can we can
start the process of taking these old
non scientific questions and making them scientific. So
so I'd echo the sentiment that,
yes, it's a messy empirical field, but
that's all also where
a lot of the possibilities,
come from. And
so, yeah, that's so I think that's
maybe that's the I think, I would
point out. Yes. Sure.
Ask and you shall receive.
Yeah. Those were all really inspiring answers.
David, your last, comment reminds me of a
of a quote often bandied around
by like sort of resentful
philosophers that everything is philosophy
until it becomes useful and then no longer
considered philosophy. And and and so
it's so exciting that we're on the
we're on the cusp, you know? Like philosophy is
more things are becoming empirically tractable.
And and they're they're bleeding into science, and it's
great. Okay.
So so now, you know,
we we all agree that that this
is an important and interesting thing
to be doing. My next question is,
how should we organize ourselves to do it?
Right? Like, I I I I've
I've I've never met a single
experienced academic who doesn't have
you know, one or two minor qualms about the
way academia is organized.
You know, or like the conference system or the review, you
know, what whatever. Right? So so my
so my my question my question for you guys is,
if you could like,
imagine someone just gave you
total power to you know, and license and encouragement
to, like, lead
a huge collaboration, restructure the fields,
you know, organize us so that we can make progress
on these questions, How should we
do it? Right? And what should we be doing differently than we're doing now if we had to reimagine
it? You wanna see? Let's actually start
with David. And go the other way. I have to give an answer to
this one. Alright. So I so I I
I'm happy with the situation.
Field. So I Okay. If anything, I think that
so I I think that the traditional
for this type of that we're facing here
in this room, I think the the
traditional academic perspective
is probably pretty productive I
think it's a time for creativity. It's a
time for new ideas. I think academia
has traditionally set up
to encourage new ideas by having
every every corner of academia you
go to you find people thinking differently
And some people, like, I, have conversations
with some professors, some postdocs,
who worry that
people use different language to do different
things. There's some disagreement of what's true
and what's not and so on. Right? There's because
because our field is so fresh, And
they they they wanna impose more order on it, They
say, let's you know, let's let's, like,
put an end to this. I think that some people
are getting funding, which they shouldn't, because
you know, people don't understand the consensus
whatever. Right? And I'm not
I I don't not sure
about that sentiment. I feel like
I feel like we don't know enough
that the the field is so fresh. It's time for creativity.
That it's okay for there to be a lot
of different ways of naming things
and lot of different ways of looking at the
same phenomena. And when when people
discover something productive,
when that idea is so good
that the idea will speak for itself. The idea will
spread. Right? Other people will adopt the
language. And and and the fact
that maybe you know, wish
it was more consensus just means that our field is still
immature. We're still looking for those productive ideas.
So so that's why I feel like, oh, yes. Not
so bad. I think there's some chaos. I wish the field
I wish the industry side of the field were
going a little slower maybe.
So that, you know, we don't have so much know, sort
of changing changing landscape
underneath our feet. But I think it's also kind
of a blessing that it's going to quickly. It makes it
exciting and it's interesting. There's always a new interesting question.
To ask. So Yeah.
Yeah. I don't have much yet. I'm also
quite happy. Actually.
Maybe the I mean, the only thing that I'm
as, you know, with my students, slightly less
happy about is is this timeline, this cycle
of every three months. Right? This is a bit of
a problem. It has an advantage because if it's
not these three months, then you tell them, you know, the idea
is not ready there's the next conference is coming in
another three months. And also the workshop system
is fantastic. I tend to come now for these workshops
more than I come from. The main
I I feel there is some sort of self
organization happening, what is
maybe annoying still is indeed
that as I mentioned the failures are not documented.
Enough. Right? Because we are benchmarks
and driven, We
keep rediscovering a lot of failures, and then I talk
to colleague and they say, yes.
Also failed on trying to do this. And then I say,
why didn't you write this down? And they said,
it's not so popular. Right? And
it's like doomed to be rejected. So
this maybe we should think about, like,
graveyard that is
visible. Of these ideas that are false
or things that didn't try. Right? This is maybe the one
thing we miss. To be Twitter.
Well, I really have nothing much to add. Maybe
when it's more question about where publications
are going since with AI, we can
write many I mean, the
number of papers written is
is becoming huge. Maybe it's about, you know, the
the time it takes to actually read some of
them that's going to be bottleneck. And,
it's I I guess at least you see some companies
may be even not you know,
going into peer review, but have
rather having blogs. And and for them, it
works visibility.
But if we go in that direction, then,
I mean, the there's a huge advantage of
being known already, and it's not really
fair. So so
how do we maintain, the publication?
Is it it going to work
long term or that's more a question.
Yeah. I'm not sure if I have any
good ideas for Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. I I will say one, I mean,
one complaint that a lot one one like problem
that a lot of maybe scientific deep
learning people have like, run into It's like
the the conference system like
conference reviewers don't always love science of
deep learning. Papers. Like, often, like,
a lot of, the
ML like,
researcher community sort of
like a popular opinion is like like I was saying in my talk
this morning. There's like two kinds of papers. There's like
theory papers which like prove theorems and are about understanding,
and then there are empirical papers, get soda.
And like don't bother
about understanding But like those are the only two buckets it's
permissible to be in. And so if
you're in that's sort of I think a viewpoint that exists.
In the field. And so I think if
you're you're paper is not in one of those buckets,
it can be like a lot of
people have found it difficult a little bit.
With our reviewers, but I I don't think there's a
fixed Yeah. May maybe just another,
theorists should stick to their guns sort of
for that one. You know. Do what they think matters.
Yeah. Okay. So this
next question is is it just really
inspired by the by the diversity of research
agendas know, on display
in the talks today. So, you know, you you guys,
you know, between you represent, like,
just in your talks, interpretability, reasoning,
like, self self learning
auto generation. It's like scaling
laws and data models and and optimization.
And, something about
something I think about, I'm curious to hear
from you guys is, these are these gonna link together
Like, is the is the plan you
know, I I when you look at a mature
discipline of science, usually
it it has a sort of like unified
feel or a comprehensive to it or something
like that.
And so I I wonder how you guys think about this. You
know, as you look forward, you think, okay, I'm
in my little pocket, but eventually, it's gonna branch
out and connect to the others, you know, like, we'll
connect to the edge of stability with neural
scaling laws
You know, what what's the end goal here? Is that
something we should be working towards now or not worried about till
later? What do you think? Think? That's
good. Let's start with Dave.
Alright. Let's start with Rich.
I mean, it it should,
You would hope, right, that there would be
some TOE
right, theory of everything that,
but that I mean,
if if you look in, there are many scientific
fields where they've been
working more than a hundred years and
they've you know, they're only part way.
Right? So I think it's
certainly something to aspire towards, but
it it's not just around the corner.
I don't quite know what to add. I think they're
not as desperate as you think.
I mean, I'm sure, you know,
you don't wanna be nailed to just
interpretability. I'm sure you have done other things.
These things are actually more connected. Like, now I work
in reasoning. I have a paper in interpretability,
for instance, and there, we just knocked
out the reasoning piece of the neural net.
Fantastic. Became two lead them. So I'm saying
there is connections between these fields, and
I we are all traveling along these various patterns,
like, big it's like a big field,
and you just grace. I I quite
happy.
Yeah. No. I I think that's
that's right. I don't know if I have a piffy
piece of advice. I'll I'll help
for a minute. Other people. To think about what
they're their answer would be. I think that
you know, my my my my emphasis
is on
gathering this empirical
view of what the structures is,
this interpretability.
And but it's I've always thought
of it as a prequel.
To understanding what
the fundamental structures
are. But it's but I think of it
as this
round through the
field with a certain type of humility.
Like, how do we know what theorem
we would even
suggest? If we haven't walked around
the town to understand the
landscape is. What kind of things are in this
town, what what what detail.
Think that it it it sometimes it feels
a little presumptuous. When
a first year PhD student comes and says, well, you know, I
think that this is the way
learning works. And and they haven't really looked around
to see what kinds of things are learned.
So I think I think that, you know,
interpret ability is,
least the way I see it,
is is a way of building
intuition. That that might empower
you to
to to, you know, raise theories in the future?
Least that's my hope.
So I think somehow this question
relates to
framework that UNIF different ideas,
and and framework will always be limited.
So, like, I can give a very subjective
answer into in terms of how do we think about
building a framework where in
my talk, we thought about scaling laws, but in
fact, we related it to the emergence
of sort of variable. That
people see in in NLMs.
And I and real have much
more complex how they
encode syntax and so so the way we are trying to do
that is to, you know, how they encode syntax and so on. So the way we're trying to do that is to, you know, develop models of
synthetic languages that are actually richer
and richer So how rich should you go? It
depends on the question you're asking.
And and what you're interested in. So so
I think that certainly makes connection between already
getting low and in top ability, but I think
with everybody, really, because if you think
about dynamics,
we will we understand the dynamics of deep
nets in in general,
it will be extremely hard. In
physics, often, we don't understand things in general. So
if you think about magnet transition,
you know, we we do understand globally
all the magnets. We started with the icing model
and then it took thirty years to develop, you
know, a group, that show
that you could classify that
many models will behave the same. So I
think we're not I mean, my my take is I mean,
my strategy that we're not yet there
are the sort of unification.
First, we have to understand simple example and
when are they useful? What are useful if they make a non
fuel prediction that you can then go and
test. And so
so in this framework, for example, if you think about dynamics
for general data, it's would be very hard. But if you
have very simple synthetic models
of say, yaki. Data, can we
understand That's what yeah.
We're some organizer. We're working on 500.
So I think that that all way to try
to
be different. Yeah. I don't have much to add, but I
yeah. I I think that everything will hope hopefully ultimately Yeah. I don't know much to add, but I Yeah. I I think that
everything will hopefully ultimately Yeah. I don't know much to add, but I Yeah. I I think that everything will hopefully ultimately Yeah. I think that everything will connect. But, yeah, I think for now, it's
sufficient I mean, I think sufficient
to just work on one direction but, like, be
aware of, like, be literate, like,
reading and keeping up with other directions
just to like look at connection.
Yeah. That makes sense. This will be the last question.
It before floor to
audience questions. So,
if you if you have had if you got a
question growing in your noggin, you
can line up behind the the
microphone.
So, yeah, the last question is,
what what open question or direction
are you
most excited about? You know, like, what what what are you obsessed
with solving if it if, if
someone told you you know, you
can only you can only solve one,
you know, you only answer one question or,
like, a satisfying answer to one open
direction in the rest of your career, like,
what what would it be? What would you want it to be?
What's the
yeah. Not at all inspired by
by AI. Getting really
good at science or Mhmm. Oh, and
let's start with Jeremy.
So I guess yeah. It's hard to
depends how I
interpret question because there's
like there's the biggest open problems
like the field. But then there's, like, when
I'm gonna work. I don't know how to so I'm
not gonna work on them. Yeah. Yeah. What I'm just
taking work on. I'll us the big
open problem. Yeah. Yeah. I'd say, like, what is feature learn? Like,
everybody knows that neural nets look work because
features. Everybody knows that. Like, in
CNNs, you have the little Gauss fielders.
And, like, in deep nets, like, people have been doing it.
Presser ball been doing, like, Meghan Turk.
What what is the what is the precise definition
of feature and what is how should we what is
the general way in which to
reason about that quantitatively? Like, no one I haven't
seen any good
answers. I'm not working on it
currently because I don't have any ideas, but, like, that's the
in my opinion, like, the one of the maybe the biggest
open problem. Yes.
So I don't want to answer in
terms of 20 I mean, like, your entire carrier
because it I mean, tends to to
change. Yeah. My my period my period
is is some shorter even though
I think the questions that now we
have new tools to address as as
was discussed before, like, how language is
encoded by machines, how does
it lead to reasoning, what's the connection with the
brain? I think, yeah,
I I I think I could spend twenty hours doing
that. I I find it really fascinating. So
maybe the more five
or five years question that
I think it's, again, relates to interpretability,
but also with the you know, so
okay. LLMs works great, but then it
10.5 data more than, than
our brand does. And so also
it seems very stupid to make prediction
that the token space Instead, you should
be predicting maybe the next idea,
And so,
and so you know, is it that
the brain also works? So so there is a
literature in ML, you know, learning from your own latent,
like data to work
and so on. But there's actually
almost zero theory, I would say.
And, and I think it's a fantastic
field because it's makes sense also that our
brain is not breaking the nice syllables that we're
saying.
I see it as another, application
of interpretability because if we
understand better what's being encoded by latent,
maybe we can make machines that are you
know, trying to predict their own latent in a better
way. That also where I
think synthetic languages can help. So I
think, this is one. Something
that's I think, very rich and
some aspect of it are essentially not studied.
Super neat. I I wanna do what you're doing.
Not what I'm doing. I I
think the fee feature learning
is extremely important. I
I To me, it's basically taking
taking any task that
deep where deep learning works
and just the simple question of
like, how how does it actually
do that? How does it implement right,
the the functions that are
needed in order to accomplish that task?
And then how were
how were the how were those functions actually
learned from the data? I mean, that's
a really like, the low level question is
really what what, continues
to excite me.
Yeah. Thanks. What's the question?
If we had one question, what would
be? Or if it Yeah. Like, the
biggest open direction. Okay. But you most excited
about? I don't reach yeah. Okay.
Mean, the question is very, scarily
formulated. Right? But nonetheless,
I think what I really want to know, and
I think we we are all I'm working on
the question. Right? Is what is intelligence?
And is this deep learning, is that really
the answer to is intelligence? And can
it really do what our brains can do? And maybe our
brains are not what is intelligence.
Right? So for me, this is it's in and
and the brain does look different from a transformer.
Right? It's does, in terms of
energy, in terms of size, in terms of
so so for me, it's it's this question of
what is intelligence, and is this thing that we have
built is it already intelligence, and what's
missing, and this kind of and whatever
comes from these questions.
Yeah. I I I
have a paper that
is not from my lab that I tell all my
students to read, and I guess maybe that's
maybe that represents the problem that I think
if I only could work on one problem. That's
that's what we should do. And
and the question is, you
know, it's related it's it's
a reason I chose the subject of the talk if
you were at the AM talk. And
the question is, you know,
how do we learn as
humans things
that are AIs
know that we don't know.
Right? Like, because these systems are
just they're It's just crazy that that we're
living in. They're so productive. They
seem to know they learn features, they
learn algorithms, and
and some of those
are likely
undoubtedly, beyond the edge of
of like sort of current human
understanding. And
and I and it just and it's just
very puzzling how
to actually
learn some knowledge, learn something substantial,
learn an algorithm that
you had no idea existed
beforehand. And so the
paper, I I I tell everybody read
Lisa Schott's
PhD thesis. She graduated
a year and a half ago, two years ago, at
t.
She worked with some deep line folks to do
this for alpha zero
chess.
To to learn what
they these things know that are beyond all
chess knowledge use. A
professional chess player herself
And and they ended up extracting
a few pieces of knowledge and teaching it
grandmasters.
I don't know how you would do it in anything other than chess.
But I I I think it's very I
think that the reason I mentioned
it is because I think
that this might be a problem that we
wrestle with as human as our
systems get big. There might be
an actual practical problem.
Of of, like, where we as
we learn to live with AI systems
that are smarter than us,
how how do we how
do we maintain our humanity? How do we maintain
our agents feel like part of that
is is cracking the puzzle of do
we learn what the AI systems know that
we don't yet know.
Know. Terrific answers. Those were all really
inspiring. Thanks. Alright.
So we're gonna, the
mic over to to that mic.
In order to get through more people,
the rules of this will be when you ask
your question, direct it towards one of the panelists.
That panelist will answer. If
anyone else wants to wants to
make add some extra comments,
you you know, you guys are you guys are free
to do that. But, I I wanna
make sure we get through a lot of the questions. So
how about it? Hello. Thank
you for the panel. So I guess I'll
ask you to professor Campe.
I wanna see so you mentioned, the thing
that difference between like theory and I guess
like science. I kinda wanted to
ask about as, like, maybe, like, other up and coming
researchers, might also feel in a similar manner.
Maybe there's like a difference between
doing science, on
the models and then, you know, perhaps
along with that pushing the intelligence frontier.
But, you know, perhaps we want to push the intelligence
frontier and we think the best way to
do that is a scientific approach. To
the research that we're doing. Right? Right? Like maybe like a brute
search. We can do a bit more principal
search over all the research that we can do.
I was wondering whether this is something
that you agree with, disagree with, what do you think about
this? And, like, how we can think about
doing research to
essentially push the frontier
of reasoning and intelligence
that can be done on silicon.
With a percival scientific approach.
That was a long question. Yeah. Thanks
for the question. So let me try to distill
your question first so.
Put it in my words. So so you're
asking what scientific principles or methods
would allow us to push the frontier
of intelligences. Is is that roughly your question?
Yes. Like, how can we take a scientific approach
to specifically push to frontier and, like, you
know, think about reasoning and,
know, how we can get that better on silicon.
Yeah. So I mean, I can only give examples for this,
but, I mean, step
one is right? This question is too abstract.
You saw my face. I was already Right? So
I would try to
find a piece of, you know, of
this phenomenon First, you know,
don't define intelligence, maybe define
you know, put something in the data and ask
can I construct a way a machine harness
or something to transcend what
I just put into my training data? Right? So make
it controllable, by controlling
all the variables that matter,
design some sort of toy, but not too
toy experiment, and then
or or theory, and then
you know, push the button, execute,
and see what happens. Right? And then reformulate
your question and and so on and
so forth. So I'm not sure this is a very satisfactory
answer, but I would not go about asking what is
intelligence, how do I push it, I would just narrow it
down to some that my
methods or my thinking can solve.
Okay. Thank you.
Hello. I'd like
to address this question to whoever feels most
inspired to answer.
There was a question, for you
all earlier about what should the ultimate goal
of a science of
deep learning be And I heard most
of you say something like, it should be
to enable practitioners.
But for me, that seems like it's just begging the question of,
like, well, why would we want that? And I would think, actually,
we want probably something like a
flufy, or something. But then
I don't know. It's something like more like you were saying at
the end felt more like the purpose.
And maybe it was, something, if I could put
it in my own words, something
like a science of the philosophy that we
care about, understanding ourselves, and also
maybe the things we're building. Maybe we don't wanna build
everything. And we can understand the optionality
of what we build. So I'm wondering,
if you agree with me, and if not, why? I'll
take I'll take
it. I I agree with you.
I, you know, I I think that,
you know, we have this
dilemma that we
are have have designed these
systems that
work better
then we know why they should.
Which is a very weird situation for
an engineer. It's not something like that. I don't know. I
was computer systems don't work. Know,
why I still can't get my printer to work you
know. You know, I I I don't know why it is.
That I, you know, I train a deep learning system and it works
better. Than I thought it
should. Why why it can solve problems that
I couldn't solve. Right? Like, how how
does how does this happen?
And and I and I so I do think that
because of this, we're confronted with this question
of how do we maintain agency, and intuitively,
it feels like understanding the
systems better
is part of that, and I think that's why. I think
that's one of the drivers behind the need
to understand the systems better.
Hello. I'm gonna direct my question.
I used to Jeremy.
Mostly written by virtue of not being David
to has already answered this question.
For a lot of people, when I talk to them about, like, science
and deep learning stuff, they
often express confusion or uncertainty about,
like, how to go about doing high
quality work. And so I was wondering if you had,
some examples of work that you can serve
particularly high quality. You'd recommend people
look at and kind of like, model
work that they do off of especially
work from outside like you and your collaborators,
because because just out of
curiosity. Yeah. No. It's definitely hard to
I mean, yeah. It's definitely hard
I find it I find it hard to do.
Work in this field.
Yeah. I'm
trying to think
Like,
I know there are a lot of promising
are a lot of direct, like, like part of like
you should you should read the
the,
position paper that Jamie
and others have recently put out
there will be a scientific theory of deep learning, which
has a lot of good leads.
But, yeah, I I find it very hard to yeah,
and also just to, like,
Yeah. It's definitely hard.
No no specific, like,
mind? Let me see. I
mean, like, what makes science of
deep learn? Like,
Yeah. I mean,
like the the mute p like the there's
like good works around MUP and related
areas that are very interesting.
Like, for example, like the, you know, the Jeremy Bernstein
line of work.
There are
I don't know. I see lots of papers every, like,
every month that I find I find at least
fascinating. I I haven't dived
deep I haven't gotten a chance to dive deep
into many
so I'm not sure which
I would
I don't have a reading list. Pre prepared reading
list. Other than the one in in the
the, position paper.
Okay. Thank you.
Oh, Dhruv Dhruv's paper is actually very
on on a I would point to Dhruvah's
paper. On, Word2vec.
Actually. Thank
you. Thanks for all your help. Which
is also getting at the question that I
understanding, like, why, linear analogies
work in word two vec.
Alright. So due to time constraints, this will be
our last question. Yeah.
Sorry. Sorry, Caden. You guys can rock, paper, scissors for
it if you want.
Thanks for the really cool panel.
I just had a question actually about a answer
that David gave earlier. About,
how one hallmark of really strong science is
that it serves as conceptual scaffolding for
future insights or future
projects or stuff like this. And maybe
this is a skill issue on my part, but I only see the
scaffolding after I've done a project, and I wanna know
if there are any concrete heuristics during
the problem selection phase that I should be
know, trying to to to steer my
interest towards something that a future
project could build on. Assuming that
things work out and stuff like that.
I don't know. Maybe I can give an example again
Sure. By example thinking, and maybe then also,
I don't know. Maybe I can give an example again by example thinking, and maybe then also, could be interpreted
as an answer. Jeremy, could have given. So
in our perspective, we can look what papers actually
had a lot of impact. That came from
with a scientific Sometimes it was the papers that
asked the question, and I'm thinking now of one
which is a very old paper. I think it was, what,
02/1718, So what
memory no. Learning
requires sorry. Understanding deep learning
requires understanding memorization. Where
they designed this where they
just mixed up all the labels, had
the training set with this, and lo and
behold, it the thing had, like, zero training wheels.
Right? Simple. Right? Afterwards.
Beautiful question. Tons of follow-up work.
I mean, people zag it all, I think. Still
cited. I don't know how many years
later, but that's in impact. Right? That's
about asking questions. So I think these kind
of things are setting
the stage also for lot of there
are many more such works. Right? In
context learning work where then there was
this thing, oh, it's like doing some sort of meta
gradient descent on the in context example It's a
whole line of works, not a I think in retrospect,
we can answer this question. Going forward, I would if I
could, I would just write. The next paper. Right?
So it's a bit
Thank you. Yeah.
But it sounds like your suggestion is simplicity.
Right? That sometimes right, so
sometimes it's not it's not the first paper to
do something. People have been digging
around an area and sometimes there's a paper that says,
oh, look at where we're all digging. Oh,
here's a simple way of looking at it. And then that's
and then that that becomes
It becomes accessible to people.
They now now people have a framework for understanding
what to think about, and I think that maybe that's
phenomena you're talking about. Right?
That could be a thing to do. So you don't
so yes. So don't don't necessarily
so I I I so
I usually tell my students
to that the way
to be risk averse
is to be creative. It's to, like, go do something
that nobody has done, like,
everybody else is afraid of. Something new. And
I usually tell them be very careful about working
in a busy area that a lot of people are in,
because it's it's harder.
To do good work. But on the other hand, if
you wanna do something really productive
sometimes, it it is to
look in a busy area and then think
about how to simplify it. And that could
be very impactful. People will be interested
in that. So yeah.
Thanks. That was really useful.
Alright. Thanks so much. Everyone, let's
give them a hand.
There's, there's one more t shirt if anyone wants to. Although,
I think it's a small.
But yeah.
Okay. So the the next thing will be,
Sara will be telling us about,
winners of our challenge.
Alright. Okay. Thank you. Thank
you all the panelists, and thank you everybody for
sticking around till the end of
today. So the last talk is
going to be in line
with the first question and answers that we got here,
actionable science. Right?
So the challenge of the workshop this
year was how can we use
our understanding, our scientific understanding
of AI to improve our models.
How can we them in practice, put this
understanding practice? The winner
this year was
paper submitted on the induction bias
in sequence models and,
we're gonna have
Reza Ibrahimi,
he's an assistant professor, in
no. There's a change of plan.
Okay.
Okay. A change of plans.
Roland, Miseveil,
Miss Servic. Was that right?
Close enough. Yes.
Okay. You very much.
So
Okay. I think this should work.
Well, thank you very much to the organizers
of this workshop for this very nice
workshop, and thank you also for
giving us this, very nice
award for, our submission.
My name is Roland Mimisiewicz. I am one of the
coauthors on this paper,
Ibrahimi, the first author on
that paper unfortunately couldn't
travel. To to ICU this year.
And so I'm going to present this work
and, it's a collaboration with
the four of us.
So, apologies ahead of time. So
I'm going to pour some cold water
on, the transformer. AGI.
It's around the corner party. I think I think
that's kind of what this work is about a
little bit.
And I'm going to present our work
that does this by,
very, very,
narrowly studying a set of tasks
that test the very specific capability
in these models, or the absence of that capability,
which is commonly referred to as state tracking.
And then, I'm gonna make
the case for recurrent nets, as a
much better model of,
both the ability to do state checking and also,
I believe, intelligence of various
kinds and especially human like, understandable,
reasonable intelligence. So there's
a very well known set of
results over the last couple of years that
has shown that autoregressive
transformers, no matter which breed
position embedding variant, whatever you wanna
consider, which size, they all
are unable to generalize very, very simple
state tracking tasks across
sequence lengths. So specifically, if you
take a task like
parody, where you have
a bunch of zeros in once, you go left to right,
you count the number of ones, and then you state in
the end whether they are odd
or even. So you do counting of the ones left
to right, module two.
It turns out that, if you so if you train that model
on a sequence length
say, 10 to 20, and then you test it on length
30, the performance sharply drops. And
so what this means is you really have to train them
on the length of the sequence that
that you wanna test them on later, and so that's true
across the board. There's just no transformer
model that is able to learn to generalize
out of distribution this way.
It doesn't change whether you do
this directly, so you ask the model to just
output the answer to the question,
or whether you allow it to do a chain of thought
or synonymously sometimes called scratch pad,
where the model goes left to right and creates
the running solution along the way. No matter
which, it just doesn't generalize out of
distribution this way.
So So what we wanted to do in this work
is to
understand whether or
not this,
inability
is really an out of distribution problem.
Or whether it's simply the absence of
an appropriate inductive bias,
that, lets the model fail. And if it's
about the inductive bias, then we would also
assume that it's not just
an out of distribution problem, but it somehow impacts
the performance of a model on this kind of task
in distribution. And so
the way, classically, in machine learning, we would study this
is by looking at the data efficiency of a
model on this kind of task. And so
in this study, we take three types of
model.
Transformer g p d two, all in the single
digit millions of parameter range.
GPD two six layers just
off the shelf kind of what was commonly used in 2019
or something like that. Then we take an
LSTM, roughly similar size, but a
single layer in this case, and we
take a dense state space model, which is specific
kind of recurrent net, the hidden to
hidden transitions are full
matrix and not a diagonal matrix. But that
include that excludes all of the
currently popular linear RNN,
state space model type models, It's a very specific
recurrent net that cannot be
parallelized, but turns out to be really, really
good for this kind of task.
So And,
so the findings in a nutshell are that,
data requirements for transformers grow
like crazy as you increase sequence lengths.
Even in distribution. And,
unlike RNNs, transformers don't really
learn to decompose this task into
a step by step computation, but
their performance is really linked
to a particular sequence length. And
so as we'll show in a second, training
a model on length five or length 10
or length 12, is
each time a completely different task for a
transformer. Whereas for an iron
in it considers all of these
sort of the same type of problem.
So here's a methodology. So the task
in this case is predominantly
modulo addition, so it's a generalization of parity,
so you have a bunch of numbers add them up.
Modulo. Five, and for
example, we consider
three supervision regimes. For these
models. One is outcome supervision, which,
is what you see on the input,
you get an equal sign, and then you just have to output
the answer. The other one is chain of thought,
which I talked to talked about
before in the case of parity. So you run you create
the running answer, and then the last
element of that will be the the the
correct final answer. And then we do another one which
we call aligned chain of thought,
which works well specifically for RNNs, where
we also do chain of thought, but the outputs
are generated along the way as you process
the sequence. And and,
we test these types of models
and and and supervision regimes
across three scenarios. We train the models
on a fixed sequence, of a
fixed length, train them on a whole
set of lengths between
two and that target length,
and we train them in a curriculum
from short to long sequences. On that
whole set. Of
lengths. And then we, so we do that in
in around 200,000 training
runs in the end, by doing a binary search
to find the optimal or
smallest number of training examples, for
which each of these models, each of these settings,
and so on is able to give us
a particular, stopping
criterion, which is like 99% or something
like that. On validation. So so I
what is the minimum of amount of data
you need to really learn this
task sufficiently and generalize in distribution?
And so here's the master table, I'm
gonna show some slices of that in a
in a second, there are several take home messages
that you can see by just kinda squinting at this.
On the top right, you see the outcomes,
so the number of training examples you need for the
transformer. On the bottom, you
see on the left LSTM, on the right, the bilinear
RNN. Slash dense state
space models. And so one thing you see
is this transformers really need chain
of thought. That's the middle row on the top
panel there.
And they do really really well on the fixed
setting. Which is
you only do the task on one sequence of
one length. Say, a length 10, and that's
it. And, you don't need to generalize across
lengths. They do
reasonably well also in the uniform setting, that's
the middle column, if you give them
a chance of thought, supervision,
but they need significantly significantly
more data, and so that setting is the one
where the model has to generalize
across all lengths up to the target lengths
in this table. And on
the very bottom, you see a line chain of
thought for the two RNN type models,
and, that's the preferred method.
For these models, and,
they don't really care that much whether it's fixed
multiple sequences, or short to long. They
always work, and they only need something
like single digit, sometimes
10, 20 training examples to work perfectly
on these tasks. So here are some
slices to to understand these tables better.
On the top left, you
see a comparison between channel
sort and aligned chain of
thought, a function of sequence lengths, and
you see that LSTMs
in blue do
much better when they get a line chain of thought. The
dashed line, and transformers
do much better when they get chain of
thought. Which is the solid line
on the top right, you see a
plot that shows us that
RNNs are much much more data efficient in the
outcome supervision case. So they can
solve the task reasonably
well with very few training examples no
matter what the sequence length is. For some
settings, and,
they don't grow much either in terms of data
needs, whereas the transformers fail already at
length 10. Plus. On the bottom left,
you see a slice that shows that
sometimes RNNs longer
sequences actually lead to a smaller
training set
requirement, and that is because
if you consider adding numbers together,
adding three numbers, adding four numbers, adding five
numbers, etcetera, are sort of always the same task.
So every step of it gives you some supervision.
Transformer just cannot catch in on
that. And, I'm gonna skip over
the last one and instead show one
more variation that we study here.
So we see that transformers kind of do
weird things when they have to generalize across multiple
sequences. Length sequence
lengths. And so to study this
a little bit more formally, we do one more thing,
which is we,
consider a setting where we have a system like
like a mixture of experts, if you will.
You take a sequence, you
depending on the sequence length, you route that
sequence to a model was only trained
for that one sequence. So you get a sequence
of length seven, you take the length seven's transformer.
Then you get a sequence of length nine, you take the length nine
transformer. This end, you have to train
one model for each sequence lengths.
And the amount of training data you need to
do that system to train the system well is
gonna be the sum in the numerator. Of that
quantity over there. And we compare
that to a model that is trained across
all sequence lengths at once.
Any reasonable model, you would assume,
is going to do better when it's trained
to course all sequences at once, because these sequences
are fundamentally identical to another. It's
just different sequence lengths. But that's
not what you see for transformers. So in the
chain of thought supervision regime, which is in
the middle, the very left plot in
the middle, you
see that the amount of data as a function
of sequence length in this experiment grows
significantly faster if you have a single
shared model than if you have an independent
model. And the exact opposite is true for the
LST LSTM. So the preferred method
there is aligned chain of thought, which is this
one. And you see that the single
shared model basically is
the multiple independent models just accumulate
more and more data because there are multiple different models.
Anyway. And we can
quantify this. This is sharing factor Kappa and
you see that RNNs have a very
high sharing factor and
factor. And since I'm running out of time, we
did this across a whole bunch of tasks, not just
module addition. But I'm gonna
conclude in the interest of time,
so I think from these experiments and similar
things that people have been showing
lately, the community one
conclusion a speculative conclusion perhaps that
we can draw from this is, in your interest of scaling,
the community
has sort of abandoned a very, very, very
natural inductive
which of the elements in a C
And, that
makes them scale well, you can train parallel and so
on, but the flip side of
that is, they also need scale. So,
even for something like adding a bunch of numbers from
zero to 10 together for a given
sequence length, you need outrageous amounts of training
data to to convey that concept. To the model.
And, so that's a very very strange thing that's just
due to the absence of that bias that
humans evidently, have, which is
true step by step processing one
one digit at a time, one one token
at a time. Recurrent
nets are a very appealing alternative.
They have other dish issues. They cannot be
trained in parallel on giant training sets and
so on.
And generally, it it raises
questions of where is this all gonna go?
And, so speculatively, what I would assume
is memory
augmented RNNs, or
hybrid models where the attention
is really, really, really short, so
it can't allow the model to learn shortcuts and
cheat its way
to to a solution on the training data might be ways.
This can unfold. But are
really early in this, it's not transformer,
don't really know what it's gonna be. And
we'll have to see for the next
few years or decades of where this can all go.
So I'm gonna finish here. I think I'm way over
time. Thank you again for this award.
And, thank you for listening.
Thank you very much.
Because we are running a bit over
time, let's so there's gonna be a
poster session and
let's ask questions during the poster session,
if you are sitting around for that. I'm
just gonna say a few words
is the first poster is a challenge,
winner poster. If you're gonna
go to that, I'm gonna say a
few words to close
the workshop.
So let's see if I
All four sticking around
on the lam.
Maybe we can't close the workshop.
Stop marrying.
So Let's play in
Alright.
Good
24, add more reps.
Hopefully, there's gonna be more iterations.
So our goal for launching this workshop
in the first place was to turn the science of
deep learning into its own
subfield. And it
feels like it's been already a a bit
effective. At least
I see more people who describe their research
as like science of deep
learning, more and more, and maybe
we can take some credit for that.
We can, a very small portion.
And but like Rich said during
the panel, this is still a very small
community. Out of all the people who
come to who come to these
major ML conferences,
only a small percentage are interested in
understanding deep nets in a
scientific way.
But, yeah.
So so most of the time, we encounter this question
that, like, why why do we
even need this? Science of deep
learning? It's a really
rich landscape, and there is a lot of so
between theory and practice, we do
need a bridge, and, there's a
lot of fun
and interesting questions that lie in this
in between of these two extremes.
And hopefully, this workshop is
one little step in getting closer
to unveil these
mysteries about deep nets.
And as we saw today,
and it was featured in the workshop, it's
an interdisciplinary risk,
effort, Really, we need, like, all of
these different perspectives from, like, signal processing
to to physics,
psychology, neuroscience, all of these people who
thought about deep nets.
To, bring their expertise
and approach it together.
Yeah. So I just wanted to
thank my, co organizers,
Thank you a lot, speakers, contributor
speakers, and all all of you who submitted
papers, to the workshop. And, hope to
see you all in the future iterations.
Thank you. And there's a poster session until
it runs until five.